<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Civil magistracy by divine authority asserted and laid forth in a sermon, preached at the assises holden at Winchester, for the county of South-Hampton, on Thursday the 4th day of March, 1651/52 : afterward the same subject much enlarged, and in some particulars more cleared, and applyed, on the like occasion, at Taunton in Somerset, on Sunday in the assize week, Aug. 22, 1652 / by William Sclater ...</title>
            <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1653</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 118 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 26 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A62375</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S914</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34025</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13661723</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13661723</idno>
            <idno type="VID">101120</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A62375)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 101120)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1047:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Civil magistracy by divine authority asserted and laid forth in a sermon, preached at the assises holden at Winchester, for the county of South-Hampton, on Thursday the 4th day of March, 1651/52 : afterward the same subject much enlarged, and in some particulars more cleared, and applyed, on the like occasion, at Taunton in Somerset, on Sunday in the assize week, Aug. 22, 1652 / by William Sclater ...</title>
                  <author>Sclater, William, 1609-1661.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 45 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by T.M. for George Treagle at Taunton and are to be sold at London by William Roybould ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1653.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Church and state --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-07</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:101120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101120:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>
               <hi>CIVIL</hi> MAGISTRACY BY DIVINE AUTHORITY, Aſſerted, and laid forth In a SERMON, Preached at the Aſſiſes holden at <hi>Wincheſter,</hi> for the County of <hi>South-Hampton,</hi> on Thurſday the 4<hi rend="sup">th</hi> day of March, 1651/52.</p>
            <p>Afterward, the ſame Subject much enlarged, and in ſome particulars more cleared, and applyed, on the like occaſion, at <hi>Taunton</hi> in <hi>Somerſet,</hi> on Sunday in the Aſſize week, Aug. 22. 1652.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>By</hi> WILLIAM SCLATER, <hi>Doctor in Divinity,</hi> Preacher of the Word of God in Broadſtreet, <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>ROM. 13.1.</hi>
               </bibl> Let every ſoul be ſubject unto the Higher Powers; for there is no power but of God: the Powers that be are ordained of God.</q>
            <q>Non ſine gravi conſilio Apoſtolus [abſtractivâ] locutione uti voluit, ut oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deret Subditos non debere ad Perſonas Imperantium reſpicere; ſed ad ipſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Officium, &amp; ad Poteſtatem, quâ divini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ùs ſunt inſtructi: Quos enim Apoſtolus hoc loco vocat <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, eos Chriſtus appellat <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Luc.</hi> 22. <hi>ver.</hi> 25. <bibl>
                  <hi>Joh. Gerard. Loc. Com. Tom.</hi> 6. <hi>cap.</hi> 1. §. 8.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>T. M.</hi> for <hi>George Treagle</hi> at <hi>Taunton:</hi> and are to be ſold at <hi>London</hi> by <hi>William Roybould,</hi> at the Unicorn in <hi>Paul's</hi> Church-yard. 1653.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:101120:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:101120:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>To the Worſhipfull JOHN TROTT, Of LAVERSTOKE Eſquire; High Sheriffe of the County of <hi>Southampton,</hi> (A moſt accompliſhed Gentleman), A full Paradiſe of Bleſſings.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S your Merits (attended with the Reputation and Honour of your Country) by the guidance of the Supreme Providence, advanced you to that preſent Station, wherein, as ſome new Beneficent Star ariſen in that Hemiſphere, you ſhine with ſo amiable Luſtre, as it powerfully at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tracts the Gordiall Regards and Love of all Eminent and Good men: So was it no meane Happineſſe to my ſelfe, that (whilſt I ſtudiouſly ſerved you) I found ſo fit an occaſion, wherein to declare my Zeal for Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſtracy, a thing ſo acceptable to God, and ſo benefi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciall to men: It pleaſed Heaven ſo far to favour my
<pb facs="tcp:101120:3"/>Endeavours this way, that my Diſcourſe gayning up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on that Honourable Aſſembly, before whom it was ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tered, was by Authority requeſted (whereas it might have been enjoyned) to the Preſs: And being thus become more publick and ſpreading, to whoſe name could I more juſtly inſcribe it, then to yours? whoſe Munificence may challenge it as a Teſtimony of my Gratitude, and whoſe Superlative Endowments, both of Nature and Grace (ſet off by ſo exquiſite Education) win it Eſteem and Acceptation abroad; Surely, under ſuch a Patronage, it cannot but be ſafe, and ſpeed the better in other hands and hearts.</p>
            <p>Two principall things there are, which render you (above others) not Commendable only, but Exempla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry; the one is, that you are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, (for Gods pure Glory ſake) a<note n="a" place="margin">1 Joh. 4.19.</note> 
               <hi>Lover of God;</hi> and the other, that you are (for pure Goodneſſe ſake) <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a <hi>Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Tit. 1.8.</note> 
               <hi>Good men,</hi> and chiefly, of Able and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Miniſters, the<note n="c" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.17.</note> 
               <hi>Men of God:</hi> Both theſe con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyned, denominate you, without either Affectation or Oſtentation, an <hi>Iſraelite</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Joh. 1.47.</note> 
               <hi>indeed.</hi> Your other Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues of Temperance, Sobriety, Manſuetude, Affa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bility, Hoſpitality, Sweetneſſe of Diſpoſition, Can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dor, Liberality, Prudence, &amp;c. all which ſo intor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>telled as they are within each other, and within you, and ſo indiſſolubly, as it were, concatenated together, they are as the Gold of<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 2.12.</note> 
               <hi>Havilah, Good;</hi> but your Piety is as the Gold of<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 45.9.</note> 
               <hi>Ophir,</hi> eximious, and<note n="g" place="margin">See Pro. 8.19</note> 
               <hi>Very Good:</hi> And were I a <hi>Chryſoſtome,</hi> and flowed with all his golden Oratory, wherein Elegantly, or
<pb facs="tcp:101120:3"/>copiouſly to embelliſh your due praiſes, I could not more graphically expreſſe you, than under that your ſo genuine Character, of being<note n="h" place="margin">Pſal. 116 16. 2 Cor. 1.12.</note> Truly, and withall moſt<note n="i" place="margin">Prov. 2.11. Pſal. 112.5.</note> Diſcreetly Religious; And as that Noble Emperour <hi>Theodoſius,</hi> thought it a greater Honor, to be <hi>Membrum Eccleſiae,</hi> then <hi>Caput Imperii,</hi> A Member of the True Church, than Monarch of the World; even ſo you doe; and may more ſolidly chear your heart in being Pious, than in being Opulent, though God hath opened both his hands, and powred forth his<note n="k" place="margin">Prov. 8.18.</note> Bleſsings upon you: And that which farther augments the Value of all, is this, that as the richeſt Carbuncles ſhine beſt in varyed lights, ſo your untainted Vertues (whilſt you keep your felf<note n="l" place="margin">Jam. 1.27.</note> unſpotted from the world) in this looſe, inconſtant and wavering Age, are diſplayed in the brighter ſplendor.</p>
            <p>How Happy then muſt your Father (to whoſe Encouragements, and Liberality I owe many Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledgements) bee eſteemed in ſuch a Son? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the ſtaffe and comfort of his old Age: I may well hither apply that Appoſite ſentence of<note n="m" place="margin">Prov. 20 7. confer Pſal 112.2, 3.</note> 
               <hi>Solomon, The juſt man walketh in his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity, and his Children are bleſſed after him:</hi> In him I cannot omit to mention one Grace (among many others reſplendent in him) re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>markeable, and that is, his ſingular<note n="n" place="margin">1 Tim. 6.16. Eccleſ. 5.18, 19</note> Contentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, accompanyed with Temperance unto Admira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>But, doubting leaſt I have exceeded the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure
<pb facs="tcp:101120:4"/>of an Epiſtle, I now betake my ſelfe to my moſt Fervent Devotions, for the accumu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of Heavens Benedictions upon your Selfe, your Vertuous Conſort, and your Hopefull Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren (encloſing alſo your worthy Parents) promi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing you to perſevere what I am,</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Sir,</salute>
               <signed>Yours, moſt Affectionately to Love and Honour you, WILLIAM SCLATER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:101120:4"/>
            <head>CIVIL MAGISTRACY BY Divine AUTHORITY.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>2 CHRON. 19.6, 7.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And he ſaid unto the Judges, Take heed what yee do: For ye judge not for man, but for the Lord, who is with you in the Judgement: Wherefore now let the fear of the Lord be upon you, Take heed and do it.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg> Shall not preſume to deteyne you by any Impertinent Preface, or as <hi>Tertullus</hi> the Orator,<note place="margin">1 Act. 24.1.</note> before <hi>Fae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lix</hi> the Governour, ſtand Court<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing your Ears this day, whereby to gain upon your Clemency to hear me a few words on this Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; ſith both the Text, and this Occaſion, like Righteouſneſſe and Peace, do ſo ſweetly embrace and kiſſe each other: The Accomodation of the one being as Conſonant to the other, as ſometimes was to the Coyn of <hi>Caeſar,</hi> the<note n="b" place="margin">Mat. 22.20, 21</note> Image of <hi>Caeſar;</hi> ſo
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:101120:5"/>that both the Importance, and withall the Seaſonable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of this Word (being like an<note n="c" place="margin">Pro. 25.11</note> 
               <hi>Apple of Gold in a Picture of ſilver</hi>) anticipates an Apology, and may well promiſe me the Favour of your Noble Patience. And indeed, as <hi>Quintilian</hi> obſerves, Where the Matter is Serious, and the Auditors indulgent, there a Proaem is uſeleſſe: Such, I am ſure, is my Matter, and ſuch, I truſt, are my Hearers: To my buſineſſe therefore.</p>
            <p>And now, as that Woman in the Goſpel, firſt lighted her<note n="d" place="margin">Luke 15.8.</note> 
               <hi>Candle,</hi> e're ſhe ſought her <hi>Groat;</hi> So, afore I come to preſent you with the Jewels, I muſt firſt open the Cabinet wherein they are lock'd up; Lead you by the Portall into the Inner Roomes; by the Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this whole Period of Scripture, direct and light you to the main Materialls of the Text.</p>
            <p>Here are many Circumſtances, and my Text like an Ingenuous Picture lookes upon all.</p>
            <p>The firſt was the <hi>Occaſion</hi> of this grave advice to the Judges; which was a Solemn Reformation both of Church and State intended by King <hi>Jehoſhaphat;</hi> in the Diamonds of whoſe Crown, though there were ſome flawes, yet the ſparkling of the one, overblazed the duskiſhneſſe of the other; for the good things found in him, <hi>ver.</hi> 3, in his hands was now intruſted the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preme Authority over the Kingdome of <hi>Judah;</hi> which Kingdome, partly through his owne Oſcitancy or Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nivence; and partly alſo (as the Story foregoing inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates) through his God-diſpleaſing League with <hi>Ahab,</hi> that Sacrilegious, Idolatrous, and Wicked Prince, ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been lately ridden with but looſe rains; He now (admoniſhed by <hi>Jehu</hi> the ſon of <hi>Hanani</hi> the Seer, <hi>ver.</hi> 2) reſolves to give a check to his foregone regardleſsneſſe, and by a ſpeedy Expergefaction, to awaken both Him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his People to a diſcreet Regulation of all paſt Diſorders.</p>
            <p>And this he ſets about in the right courſe, and after the beſt order: He begins firſt with Himſelf; next with
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:101120:5"/>Religion; and then with Civill Juſtice, as the ſtrong Guard to both.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. With <hi>Himſelfe;</hi> And as the<note n="e" place="margin">Prov. 30.28</note> Spider taketh hold with her hands, and begins to mend her Web at the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle, He prepared his [Heart] to ſeek God, <hi>ver.</hi> 3. By which Perſonall Reformation, the Vertue of his Pious Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple proved ſo Magneticall, that it attracted the Obſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation of all his People; He went out again through the people, from <hi>Beerſheba</hi> to Mount <hi>Ephraim:</hi> The An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cients were wont to place the Statues of their Kings by Springs or Fountains; to intimate, as one obſerves, that they were the Fountains of Good or Ill in a Common Wealth; So was <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> here, of good, to his Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects.</item>
               <item>2. Next to <hi>Himſelf,</hi> and his owne Heart and Actions, He takes care immediately for <hi>Religion,</hi> and the right Worſhip of the true God; and ſurely, none ſo fit to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtore that, as they who firſt have made their own hearts as it were, the mould, wherein to caſt Religion as in the proper Form; and ſurely, thus did <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> as is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bundantly manifeſt in the twentieth Chapter enſuing, by his Faſting and Praying, and ſeeking of God; ſo that as ſoon as his heart had<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 45.1.</note> indited ſo good a Matter, his tongue incontinently becoms <hi>as the pen of a ready writer;</hi> By an effectuall Invitation reducing his Exorbitant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from their Adoration of Idols in their Groves, unto the Veneration of the True God in <hi>Jeruſalem;</hi> He brought them back unto the Lord God of their Fathers, <hi>ver.</hi> 4.</item>
               <item>3. After himſelfe and Religion, having ſo well entred with God; He then, and not till then, provides for <hi>Civil Juſtice,</hi> and the due adminiſtration thereof, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the rules of Equity and Judicious Reaſon throughout the Land; and this to be managed by ſuch Perſons, whoſe Learning and Experience in the Lawes, ſhould give weight to their Proceedings, whoſe Age and Gravity win Reverence and Honour to their Perſons;
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:101120:6"/>ſuch as theſe <hi>He ſet Judges in the Land, throughout all the fenced Cities of Judah, City by City,</hi> ver. 5. and ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving given them their Commiſſion, and withall ponde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red the ſeriouſneſſe of the Employment; <hi>He ſaid to the Judges, Take heed what yee do, for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord, &amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>And thus I have ſhewen you the ſeverall Circumſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of this Scripture, which, were it, happily, in a skilful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler hand, might yet be branch'd out farther into more variety: But leaſt I may ſeem to have hovered too long in the Air of Generalities, I ſhall now faſten on thoſe Subſtantiall Materialls which are here before us in the Text.</p>
            <p>Which Text is as the ſhort abridgement, or Epitome of what concerns the Magiſtrate, as ſuch, in the diſcharge of that Function; inſomuch, that whatſoever lines of Paticularities can be drawn from the largeſt Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, may be all here concentred in this Point: Yet for my Method in the preſent Sermon, I obſerve out of it, theſe Heads of Diſcourſe.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1.<note place="margin">The Diviſion</note> The <hi>Office</hi> it ſelfe, <hi>Ye Judge,</hi> or <hi>Judge ye.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2 The <hi>Authority</hi> or <hi>Commiſſion</hi> by which they exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute that Office, <hi>Not for man, but for the Lord; Vices Domini gerentes,</hi> as <hi>Junius</hi> notes, As God's Vice-gerents.</item>
               <item>3. The <hi>Diſcharge</hi> of that Office, <hi>Do it,</hi> or <hi>Judge ye; Judicabitis, Ye ſhall Judge,</hi> ſo tranſlated in the Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, hath, after the Hebrew Idiotiſme, the Vertue of an Imperative.</item>
               <item>4. The due <hi>Caution</hi> or <hi>Circumſpection</hi> to be heeded in that Diſcharge, <hi>Cavete, Take heed;</hi> which is twice repeated, both in the Front, and in the Foot of the Text; The one ſtanding as an <hi>Ecce,</hi> prefix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the other, as one of <hi>David</hi>'s <hi>Selahs,</hi> ſubjoyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; both which Notes, ſerve to ſet an Accent up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Obſervation: The former <hi>Cavete</hi> hath re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation to the Matter, <hi>Take heed what ye do.</hi> The
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:101120:6"/>later <hi>Cavete</hi> hath reſpect to the Manner, <hi>Take heed Now, let the fear of the Lord be upon you.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>5. The <hi>Motive</hi> to perſwade the well accompliſhed diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>charge of the whole, <hi>Vobiſcum Jehovah in rebus Judiciariis; God is with you in the Judgement,</hi> or <hi>in the matter of Judgement:</hi> Which phraſe of Gods being <hi>[with them]</hi> is in travell, as <hi>Rebekah,</hi> with a Twin of Interpretations; It denoting, either God's preſence, as a <hi>Spectator;</hi> or elſe God's pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heminence, as a <hi>Protector</hi> of you in the matter of Judgement; Which later ſeems by the laſt words of this Chapter to be the moſt genuine, where he ſaith, <hi>Deal couragiouſly, and the Lord ſhall be [with] the Good,</hi> to wit, for their Divine Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtance.</item>
            </list>
            <p>And theſe (at leaſt as to my obſervation they occurr) are the proper parts of this Scripture, the meaſures of my Sermon, and of your Chriſtian Patience: Pleaſe to favour me with the one, whilſt I am, by Gods bleſſing, in the diſpatch of the other, I ſhall be as compendious as the Gravity of this matter, and the great affairs enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſhall allow in all.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And he ſaid to the Judges, Take heed what ye do,</hi> &amp;c.<note place="margin">The firſt part</note>
            </p>
            <p>The firſt member of my Diviſion mentioned, is the <hi>Office it ſelf of Magiſtracy,</hi> which I apprehend may well be couched under the Term or Style of Judging, an e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minent degree of the ſame: From whence the Point that I would commend to you, is this, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>The Office and Benefit of Government,</hi>
               <label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Doctrine. </seg>
               </label> 
               <hi>together with the miſchief and miſery of Anarchy.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In ſpeaking whereof, I ſhall uſe the ſame modeſt A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pology, which<note n="g" place="margin">Calv. <hi>Inſtit. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>c.</hi> 20. §. 9.</note> Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi> (that bright burning Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per of <hi>Geneva</hi>) did, being about to write upon the ſame Subject: In Expounding (ſaith he) the Magiſtrates Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, <hi>Non tàm Magiſtratus ipſos inſtituere conſilium eſt, quàm alios docere quid ſint Magiſtratus;</hi> It is not my
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:101120:7"/>intention to informe the Rulers, or Magiſtrates them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves; but to inſtruct others of the people, who are to be Ruled and Governed by them, What the Magiſtrates are, and for what good end and purpoſe they are ordei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned of God himſelfe: Not to informe them, this were for me (under this Station) to exceed the activity of my own proper Orb, and to move in the Excentricks; yea, this were after a ſort to blend Profeſſions, and to mingle Civil Judicatures with Theologicall Doctrines; to fetch that into the Pulpit, which is proper only, and adaequate to the Bench; my Office is to teach others the great benefit, and good that God by the Ordinance it ſelf of Magiſtracy intendeth, and doth; this, under favour (in a Spirituall notion) appertains to our Miniſtry, the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to excite the people to their duty, both of Prayer and Praiſes for them, and of conſtant fidelity to them.</p>
            <p>Now, Two things there are that muſt come under this Head. Firſt, the <hi>Office</hi> or <hi>Government</hi> it ſelf. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, The <hi>Beneſit,</hi> and <hi>Advantage</hi> of the ſame. Theſe two like<note n="h" place="margin">1 King. 7.21</note> 
               <hi>Jachin</hi> and <hi>Boaz</hi> in <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple, are the two main Pillars, ſupporting the whole Fabrick of my ſpeech; and in my ſpeaking of them, I ſhall of neceſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty ſo twiſt my Diſcourſe with the Benefit, that, as that Artificer wrought his own name ſo cunningly in the Buckler of <hi>Minerva,</hi> that it could not be pick'd out, without the diſſolution of the whole Frame; ſo take out the name of Benefit from Government, the moſt beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull frame of any State may ſoon lye in the duſt.</p>
            <p>The firſt thing that I ſhall endeavour is, to ſhew you the nature of Magiſtracy, what it is: and thus I ſhall de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Magiſtracy is a publick Power ordeined of God,</hi>
               <note place="margin">What Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtracy is.</note> 
               <hi>for the preſervation of Order, Diſcipline and Peace in a Common Wealth, by Encouragement of the Good, and by the Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhment of Evill and Contumacious Perſons, according to Juſt Lawes:</hi> This is Magiſtracy in it ſelf.</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:101120:7"/>1. Magiſtracy is a <hi>Power,</hi> ſo ſtyled by the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the word ſignifies, <hi>a Power of Right and Authority,</hi> which makes it to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> High and Supereminent above others; ſo that the very terme of Relation implieth the order of Superiority, and of In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriority; High and Low, the Scripture mentions, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 62.9. and 49.2. <hi>Small and Great, Act.</hi> 26.22. <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.12. The one, in a rationall apprehenſion, ſuppoſeth the other; For, <hi>Par in parem non habet proteſtatem;</hi> if a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt levelling Equals none may challenge to Rule the reſt, then the very name and nature of Government doth inforce an inequality: And indeed, without this, there could be nothing but confuſion in the world; For what is<note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>Biſh.</hi> Dave<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant, quaeſt. <hi>42.</hi> pag. <hi>187,</hi> Edit. <hi>1634.</hi> Cantabr.</note> Order? But <hi>Parium, impariúmque ſua cuique tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buens loca diſpoſitio;</hi> A meet diſpoſition of Equalls, and Unequalls, giving unto each their proper and due pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces; and without ſuch a moderate and meet Imparity, the<note n="k" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ariſtot. l. <hi>1</hi> cap. <hi>5.</hi> Polit.</note> Community will ſuffer: Government, it's as or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to an army, which without it were but a crowd; it's as an hedge to a Vineyard, which without it, would be waſted by Wild Boars, and other ſpoiling Creatures; it's as an hemn to a garment, which without it would ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vell out; Hence was that known ſaying of<note n="l" place="margin">Greg. Naz. lib. <hi>3.</hi> Theolog.</note> 
               <hi>Nazianzene,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Anarchy is ever Diſorder; And that freedome muſt of neceſſity be moſt unfree, which under a<note n="*" place="margin">Du Moulin, <hi>Defence of King James,</hi> Art. 22.</note> Title of Liberty introduceth licentiouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, wherein whilſt every one would be chief, he be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comes a ſlave to himſelfe, and to every one: Now ſuch impetuous diſorders, where ever they ariſe, if by any thing, will be by Government removed, or at leaſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verawed: This was not impertinently ſet forth by the Ancients (ſaith<note n="m" place="margin">L<hi rend="sup">d</hi>. Verul. l. <hi>1</hi> Advancement of Learning.</note> one) in that faigned relation of <hi>Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheus</hi> Theatre, where all Birds aſſembling, and forget<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting their ſeverall appetites, ſome of Prey, ſome of Game, ſome of Quarrell, ſtood all ſociably together, liſtening unto the ayres and accords of the Harp; the ſound where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of no ſooner ceaſed, or was drowned by ſome louder
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:101120:8"/>noiſe, but every beaſt returned to his own nature again. Wherein is aptly deſcribed the nature and condition of men, who are full of Savage and unreclaimable deſires, of Profits, of Luſt, of Revenge; which as long as they give ear to Religious Precepts, and to good Lawes, ſweet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly touch'd with Eloquence, and Perſwaſion of the Makers, ſo long is Society and Peace maintained; but if theſe Inſtruments be ſilent, or that Sedition and Tumult make them not audible, all things diſſolve into Anarchy and Confuſion; We need ſeek no farther for this, then the Book of <hi>Judges,</hi> where, under the want of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, every man did what was good in his own licen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious eye;<note n="n" place="margin">Judg. 17.6. &amp; 21.25.</note> and that, I am ſure, was crooked in God's ſtrict eyes: There was the Corruption in Religion, in the making and worſhipping of a Graven Image, horri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note n="o" place="margin">Judg. 17.4, 5.</note> Idolatry, by <hi>Micah</hi> and his mother; there was Burglary, Robbery, and rifling of Houſes, yea, whole Cities of Harmeleſſe Poor people, and cutting all their<note n="p" place="margin">Judg. 18.27.</note> throats; abominable plundering, and lewdneſſe by the men of <hi>Dan:</hi> There was (ô Prodigious Act!) the ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhing of a woman, and that to death, <hi>chap.</hi> 19. by the men of <hi>Gilead,</hi> who alſo faced it out with impudence, and ſtood to maintain it; upon the matter, there are no<note n="*" place="margin">It was a ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing under <hi>Ner<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>va,</hi> It was bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter to live where nothing, then where all things are law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full.</note> worſe things in the world, then theſe were; yet all theſe were the iſſues of Anarchy in thoſe dayes: The people likewiſe in the<note n="q" place="margin">Exod. 32.</note> abſence of <hi>Moſes</hi> the chief Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernour, were as a ſhip wanting a Pilot at ſea, and ſo ran upon the rock of Idolatry, in making them an Idoll the Calfe of <hi>Egypt:</hi> And I marvell, were there no Seſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions or Aſſizes, or Courts of Judicature and Juſtice in our dayes, if the whole Land, like that of <hi>Egypt,</hi> would not ſwarm with<note n="r" place="margin">Exod. 10.5.</note> Locuſts and Caterpillats, with Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>throats, Robbers, Outragious Vagabonds; and Male<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors, which now (bleſſed be God) by the beeſome of Circuit Juſtice are ſwept off (what may be) from our earth.</p>
            <p>Wherefore it was wittily obſerved by <hi>Hermes Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megiſtus,</hi>
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:101120:8"/>or whoſoever was the Authour of that Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue, which paſſeth under his name;<note n="ſ" place="margin">Hermes Triſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>megiſt. Dialog. <hi>9.</hi> ad Aeſculap.</note> that by the Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cians, the world was ſtiled, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, that is, Faire: [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, For that God and Nature had ſo beauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied and a dorned it, not only with variety in the produ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction of the Creatures, but in the comely order of whatſoever was made, by a decent ſubordination of one unto the other. Government was at firſt founded in Paradiſe immedately upon the Creation; <hi>Dominamini,</hi> ſaith the Lord to <hi>Adam, Gen.</hi> 1.28. <hi>Have dominion over every living thing;</hi> yea, 'tis accorded by<note n="t" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Joh. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard.</hi> loc. Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mun. Tom. <hi>6.</hi> cap. <hi>2. § 25.26</hi> &amp;c. S. <hi>Aug.</hi> de Civit. Dei l. <hi>19.</hi> c. <hi>15.</hi>
               </note> Divines moſt Orthodox, that however in the ſtate of innocence there was not, nor ſhould not have been any deſpoticall, or Imperious coercive domination, as is now ſince the Fall, of one man over another; ſo that, then, one ſhould have born the ſway, <hi>cum libidine dominandi,</hi> with an ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tious luſt or deſire to compell others as inferiour; yet, even then, under that very ſtate, there would have been a fatherly, or oeconomicall ſubordination in Families, and Societies of mankind, joyned with a ſpontaneous, voluntary yeildance, as it were, through an innate <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or naturall Inſtinct, to the mutuall counſelling and lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of each other; as Husband and Wife, Father and Child, Neighbour and Neighbour, for the Glory of God, and their own Beatitude. Thus the Schoolmen (among whoſe Diſputes, though there be found much Droſſe of Superſtition, yet withall, ſome Gold of pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious and refined Wit) they directly pronounce thus, <hi>Fuiſſet in ſtatu innocentiae praelatio in officio conſulendi, &amp; diligendi, non Dominium ſervituti oppoſitum,</hi> as <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mas, Biel,</hi> and others to the ſame Effect, expreſſe it: Yea, this may be yet read farther in the Book of the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Creatures themſelves, which are indeed halfe loſt, if we only employ them, and learn nothing of them; <hi>Totus mundus nihil aliud eſt, niſi Deus explicatus,</hi> ſaith <hi>Cuſanus:</hi> The whole Macrocoſm, or bigger world, is but a
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:101120:9"/>book unclaſp'd, wherein are the expreſſe characters of Gods Divine Wiſedome ſhining in that order, wherein he firſt created it; even that God, who by the great Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtle, who was ſo much for decency and order in the Churches, is directly ſtiled, not the Authour of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, but the God of Peace, and order, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.33. Yea, meditate but what is written of thoſe, who never yet ſtained the honour of their Primitive Creation, ſtill keeping their firſt eſtate, not leaving their own<note n="u" place="margin">S. Jude <hi>ver.</hi> 6</note> Habita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; look upwards in Heaven, among the confirmed Angels, there are Degrees: <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <hi>Damaſcen.</hi> lib. <hi>2.</hi> Orthodox. Fid. cap. <hi>3.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Damaſcen,</hi> accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their light and ſtation, ſo is their Priority; There are, ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Mights and Dominions, <hi>Principalities and Powers, Epheſ.</hi> 1.21. <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.38. Yea, among that Sacred Hierarchy, Saint <hi>Jude</hi> aſſures us, <hi>ver.</hi> 9. there is <hi>Michael</hi> an Archangel; to omit any farther enumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of more orders of them, after the Computation of <hi>Dionyſius Areopagita,</hi> an Author, however ſaid to be ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitious, as reckoned among Saint <hi>Paul</hi>'s Converts, <hi>Act.</hi> 17.34. yet yeilded to be of long antiquity. Again, from thoſe Heavens, let us behold the Starry Firmament, and there we diſcover two great Luminaries, as<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 136.8, 9</note> Rulers of the times and Seaſons, <hi>the Sun to rule the Day, and the Moon the Night.</hi> Look yet below theſe into the Ae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theriall Heavens, and there we find the<note n="y" place="margin">Horat.</note> Eagle ſoaring aloft and prevailing:<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Plin.</hi> l. <hi>10.</hi> cap. <hi>23.</hi> Nat. Hiſt.</note> 
               <hi>Pliny</hi> writes of Cranes, birds of a ſubordinate feather, <hi>Ducem quem ſequantur, eligunt,</hi> they ſelect a guide: Upon the earth, among Beaſts, the Lion; among Trees, the Cedar overtops: If we go down to the<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 107.23.</note> ſea in ſhips, and occupy our buſineſſe in the great waters, even there find we a<note n="b" place="margin">Pſal. 104.26.</note> Leviathan to take his paſtime: In a word, Take view of the Microcoſme, or little world, man himſelf, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Ariſtot. <hi>l.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>Polit.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Ariſtottle,</hi> the ſoul commands the body, and the mind in the ſoul it ſelfe, the ſenſuall appetite, and all the Inferiour Powers in the ſame: Yea, I had almoſt added,
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:101120:9"/>if we caſt our eyes downwards, even in the pit of dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, the<note n="d" place="margin">Rev. 12.9.</note> Dragon hath his Angels, and there are or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, and<note n="e" place="margin">Mat. 12.24.</note> degrees, even in the Region of Confu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>What ſhould I ſay more? Wherefore, though my heart be much enlarged, and my thoughts voluminous in this matter, yet being ſtraitned in the bowels of the time, as <hi>Homers Iliads</hi> were (once) preſented to a great Potentate in a nut-ſhel; ſo I muſt now be forced to epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tomize my expreſſions in a word or two: Take it in the Oratours own lines, <hi>Omnem naturam,</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Cic. de Nat. Dcor. lib. <hi>2.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>quae non eſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plex, ſed cum alio conjuncta, neceſſe eſt habere aliquem in ſe principatum;</hi> that is thus much in the ſenſe, Every created nature capable of Society, of neceſſity, muſt have in it ſome Superiority. Formes of Government (its un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>denyable) have been in ſeverall ages and revolutions of time, divers in the world, according to Gods own pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>found and providentiall Diſpenſations; and withall, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording as his own Divine Wiſdome foreſaw to be beſt for his own Church and people; and under the <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the very act of the time of mutation, the alteration of Governments (yea or but the ſucceſſion of Gorvernors) is, ſaith one, oft times, like the removing of the world from one ſhoulder of <hi>Atlas</hi> to another, which occaſions Epilepſies, and ſhakings in the earth; nor is it eaſie, at the firſt, for men to pronounce their <hi>Shibboleth</hi> of new Titles, and names accompanying ſuch alteration: For a long time the Government was Patriarchall, or Father<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, rather then Princely, as during all their ſtaying in <hi>Egypt,</hi> when yet they were growen into the body of a Nation numerous and mighty: After that, even in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naan,</hi> governed they were long by Judges, by advice of the High Prieſt, and that about the ſpace of four hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred and fifty years, as we read <hi>Act.</hi> 13.20. untill <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> the Prophet: After that, God gave them <hi>Saul</hi> a<note n="g" place="margin">1 Sam. 8.</note> King, a man of <hi>Benjamin,</hi> in anger, and took him a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in wrath, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13.11. Briefly, the<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtot. <hi>lib.</hi> 8. <hi>Polit. cap.</hi> 10.</note> Forme was
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:101120:10"/>ſometimes <hi>Democraticall,</hi> ſometimes <hi>Ariſtocraticall,</hi> other whiles <hi>Monarchicall:</hi> But (things here below be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing in a perpetuall gyre of mutation) <hi>doth the Crown endure to every generation?</hi> Prov. 27.24. Even the moſt laſting Kingdomes have had their<note n="i" place="margin">See B. <hi>Hall,</hi> Serm. on <hi>Pſal.</hi> 107.34. <hi>p</hi> 10.</note> Period; and of the moſt ſettled Government, Gods hand writing upon the wall goes ſo far, as to ſay, <hi>Mene, Mene,</hi> Thy dayes are numbred: That<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 75.6, 7.</note> God, he who alone it is that putteth down one, and ſetteth up another,<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 59.13.</note> 
               <hi>Ruleth in Jacob,</hi> and even unto the ends of all the earth, ſitting upon the circle thereof, as the Prophet expreſſeth it, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 40.22. and as we read <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.45. that the ſtone cut out of the moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tains without hands brake in pieces the Gold, and the Silver, the Braſſe and the Iron in the great Image, that is Chriſt, the<note n="m" place="margin">Eph. 2.20.</note> 
               <hi>Head ſtone of the corner,</hi> born, unuſual<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, of an incontaminate Virgin, overcame by the Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of his power, the four great Monarchies of the world. <hi>Aſſyrian, Perſian, Grecian, Roman,</hi> and ſhall doe the Papall alſo; and the ſame Prophet again, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.17. The living muſt know, that the moſt High ruleth in the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of men, and he giveth it to whomſoever he will: This is the Lords doing and it is marvellous in all mens eyes. But yet, (which is the totall of what I aim at) in the great change of times and Seaſons, in the altera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of various formes, nevertheleſſe the God of order upholdeth the State or Government it ſelf, which (as I noted in the firſt branch of the Deſcription) was a Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, and that an High and Supereminent Power; and thoſe Powers that are, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in preſent, actuall being, the ſame are not without Gods own ordination, as I ſhall forthwith demonſtrate; and to thoſe preſent Powers in act (commanding lawfull things) men muſt be ſubject, even for conſcience of God, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1.5.</p>
            <p>But ere I go on to that, I may not omit the Epithet, or (if you will call it ſo) the Adjunct of this Superemi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Power: It is not a private, but a publick Power; that is, a Power Authorized by a Lawfull Commiſſion to
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:101120:10"/>execute, as the Lords avengement of ſin,<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Auguſtin. contr. Fauſt. Manich. l. 22. &amp; 77. c 70.</hi> Ille abutitur gladio, qui nulla Superiori, ac le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gitimâ pote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate vel juben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, vel conceden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te, in ſanguinem alicujus arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur— Nam u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tique Dominus juſſerat, ut fer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Diſcipuli ejus ferrent, ſed non juſſerat, ut ferirent. Vid <hi>Rayner.</hi> de Piſis Pan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theol. tom. <hi>1.2.</hi> &amp; Thom. <hi>2<hi rend="sup">a</hi>,</hi> 2ae, Qu. <hi>40.</hi> Art. <hi>1.</hi>
               </note> Juſtice and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon arraigned and convicted Malefactors; for o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therwiſe, as our Saviour ſaid to <hi>Peter,</hi> all they that <hi>take the ſword, ſhall periſh with the ſword,</hi> Mat. 26.52. that is, as all Orthodox Divines expound it, All they who take the ſword to ſmite withall, out of their own voluntary, pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate motion, to ſatisfie their own private revenge, theſe ſo ſinning without Authority, ſhall for that ſin be ſmit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten by the publick ſword: which, by juſt Authority, is put into the hands of Lawfull Magiſtrates, as God's Vice-gerents upon earth, to execute and repay God's Juſt and Publick revenge upon Offendors: In <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.6. we read, <hi>Who ſo ſheddeth mans blood</hi> (to wit, by a pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate ſword, that makes it Murder) <hi>by man ſhall his blood be ſhed,</hi> namely, by a publick ſword of the Magiſtrate, who bears it not in vain, but to be unſheath'd and u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, which makes it Juſtice; Magiſtrates are not <hi>Homi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cidae,</hi> but <hi>Malicidae,</hi> as<note n="o" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bern.</hi> de Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lite, fol. <hi>109.</hi> m. Object.</note> 
               <hi>Bernard</hi> wittily.</p>
            <p>If any liſt to object the Act of <hi>Phineas</hi> a Prieſt, and no Civill Magiſtrate, commended for his Zeal in ſlaying <hi>Zimri</hi> and <hi>Cosbi,</hi> under their ſin, <hi>Numb.</hi> 25.8. as like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe the example of <hi>Samſon,</hi> by <hi>ſuicide,</hi> deſtroying himſelfe, and with himſelf, both his own, and Gods e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, <hi>Judg.</hi> 16.30. Yet he is numbred among the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.32. and ſo capable of imitation?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> To this the Reſolution is,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> that <hi>Motus Heroici non ſunt in imitationem trahendi,</hi> thoſe Heroicall moti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, as (for diſtinction ſake) Divines do ſtyle them, were Perſonall Diſpenſations, daigned out of ſingular Priviledge, and ſo are reſtrictive to them alone, and ſuch as are guided, upon like aſſurance, by like warrantable inſtinct from God, and ſo not to be drawn into ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary imitation. The examples even of Saints themſelves <hi>Contra datam legem,</hi> if they do not (as) Saints, but de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viate from the generall Rule, muſt be declined: now, the knowne rule is,<note n="p" place="margin">Deut. 32.35 Rom. 12.19.</note> 
               <hi>Vengeance is mine, and I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pay it,</hi> ſaith the Lord Himſelfe, who executeth the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:101120:11"/>ſame by the ſword, put into the hand of his owne Ordinance, the Publick Magiſtrate, The Higher Powers.</p>
            <p>By this time I preſume, the beames of Order and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment it ſelfe, by Arguments drawn both from Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture and Grace, from Reaſon and Religion, ſhine clearly upon all bright and ſolid underſtandings: And yet (wo is me!) I cannot diſſemble what black and pitchy Clouds have been interpoſed between this ſerene light, and the minds, at leaſt, the refractary wills of ſome, whom I cannot better compare, then to looſe teeth in a mans head, being often more troubleſome, then uſeful to Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill Society: However, with<note n="q" place="margin">3 Ep. Job. 9.</note> 
               <hi>Diotrephes,</hi> they may de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire preheminence, and would be ſome body in the trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, who (it may be) were as no body in the peace of the Church.</p>
            <p>Thus they pretend,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Object. </seg>
               </label> wreſting the Scriptures, as Saint<note n="r" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaks, to their own hurt, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, dealing like Chymicks, who labour to torture nature, for the extraction of ſuch ſpirits, as were never inherent in the thing: Its ſaid, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.28. and <hi>Col.</hi> 3.11. <hi>There is nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther bond nor free, Jew nor Greek, but all are one,</hi> under the New Teſtament, in Chriſt Jeſus, who is all, and in all?</p>
            <p>But for anſwer:<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſw. </seg>
               </label> What think they? Is there no diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence in any reſpect? Belike then, a man muſt leave his Nation, <hi>Jews</hi> muſt be no <hi>Jews,</hi> nor <hi>Grecians, Grecians.</hi> In ſhort, the right meaning is this; In reſpect of Spiritu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all ſtate and Title to Chriſt, all are one, Servants as well as Maſters, ſmall as well as great, they have <hi>obteined the [like precious] faith,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.1. and ſhare together in the <hi>[common] faith, Tit.</hi> 1.4. Becauſe Faith and Piety, and ſuch graces are inward matters of the ſoul, tending to the better life (and in ſuch Gratuities there cannot be ſaid to be properly any partiality in God, or any<note n="ſ" place="margin">Rom. 2.11.</note> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of perſons on Gods part) yet in reſpect of civil and outward condition, remaines the ancient difference
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:101120:11"/>of Rulers and Obeyers, of Maſter and Servant; or if there be any other externall thing, whereby they are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtinguiſhed one from the other: Beſides, that Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Liberty, whereby Chriſt hath made us free from the rigorous exaction of the<note n="t" place="margin">Gal. 5.1.</note> Law, and from the power of ſin and Satan, doth not at all intrench upon that Order, and thoſe Civill Degrees which he hath moſt comely e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtabliſhed in the world: A Politick Inaequality is not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Spirituall Aequality; <hi>Oneſimus</hi> (ſaith a Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy<note n="u" place="margin">Mr. <hi>Joſiah Shute,</hi> the <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> of his time, <hi>pag.</hi> 132. <hi>Ser<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>on</hi> Gen. 16</note> Divine now with God) was as good as <hi>Philemon</hi> in Chriſt; yet, for all that, <hi>Oneſimus</hi> was <hi>Philemon</hi>'s ſervant. Wherefore, amongſt other gifts given to the Church, theſe are ſome, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12.28. Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernments; that is, gifts enabling to govern, to the intent they may be exerciſed; God and Nature do nothing in vain, neither doth he gift a man for any thing unlawful, nor would ſo many Godly men have taken on them the managing of that Office, had it been other then ſuch as was, and is allowed by God.</p>
            <p>Beloved Chriſtians, give me leave to ſpeak my mind freely to you, (and <hi>I</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 7.40.</note> 
               <hi>think alſo, that I have the Spirit of God</hi> directing me herein) It is to be ſuſpected, that all ſuch <hi>Samſons,</hi> who would thus<note n="x" place="margin">Judg. 16.9.</note> tear the withs of Government aſunder, and attempt the exauctorating all Civill Magiſtracy, doe it onely, that with the more ſecurity they may cocker the wanton <hi>Delilah's</hi> of their own corrupt Natures, that chafe moſt under the bit, fretting at what may bridle or curb the carnality of the ſame; in their lives; ſome of them are as unclean lepers as ever ſore ran upon. Such ulcers (or rather, plagueſores) brake out, and, I am ſure, ran with the pernicious infection of many in <hi>Germany,</hi> not above an Age paſt, that as<note n="y" place="margin">Sleidan <hi>l.</hi> 5. &amp; 10. <hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentar.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Sleidan,</hi>
               <note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Bullinger</hi> Contra Anabap.</note> 
               <hi>Bullinger, Calvin,</hi> and others record the luxury of their reaking Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſation, it appears, that they were, of all men, ſuch as had moſt need of Government: However, till the Juſtice of Heaven ſtopp'd them, they<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 2.3.</note> 
               <hi>threw off the
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:101120:12"/>yoak</hi> of the Lawes, and following the float of their own<note n="b" place="margin">Jude ver. 8.</note> 
               <hi>filthy dreams,</hi> they <hi>turned the grace of God into</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Jude ver. 4.</note> 
               <hi>wantonneſſe, deſpiſed</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.10.</note> 
               <hi>Dominion, and ſpake evill of Dignities;</hi> thoſe ambitious <hi>Nimrods,</hi> who would have pull'd down <hi>Sion,</hi> to build up <hi>Babel.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But leaving this jarring Diſcourſe about ſuch <hi>vaine</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 1.6.</note> 
               <hi>janglers</hi> as thoſe were then, (and if any are found of the ſame miſſe-inclinations now) to <hi>wallow</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">2 Pet. 2.22.</note> 
               <hi>in their own mire,</hi> till their abominable wickedneſſe be<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 36.2.</note> found out to be hatefull: I ſhall now ſet the ſtrings of my ſpeech to a more pleaſing tune, that it may ſound with more harmony in your ears: Whileſt, in the next place, I ſhall preſent my Hearers with the great Benefits and Advantages that by Government they may enjoy.</p>
            <p>And theſe being in ſo multiplicious a variety,<note place="margin">The Benefits of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment.</note> I muſt be forced to do as Lapidaries of rich Jewels are wont, ſhew them onely in a ſhort glance, and ſo lay them up again.</p>
            <p>And now, What<note n="g" place="margin">Hoſ. 12.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſimilitudes</hi> ſhall I borrow to il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrate this Bleſſing? We may ſooner beggar the whole Exchequer of Nature, or impoveriſh Wealth it ſelf, then from thence be able to fetch a meet compariſon for its complete embelliſhment. Lo! The<note n="h" place="margin">
                  <hi>Char. lib.</hi> 1. <hi>c.</hi> 49. §. 1.</note> 
               <hi>State,</hi> that is to ſay, Rule, Dominion, or a certain order in Commanding and Obeying, is the prop, the cement, and the ſoul of Humane things: it is the bond of Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, which cannot otherwiſe ſubſiſt: it is the very vitall ſpirit whereby ſo many millions of men do breathe, and the whole Creation hath a wel-being. Tell me, What is it that cloathes you in<note n="i" place="margin">2 Sam. 1.24.</note> 
               <hi>Scarlet,</hi> with other delights, and puts on ornaments of gold upon your apparel; is it not Government? What is it that cloathes your Downs, your Paſtures, your Valleys with Flocks and Store, till they<note n="k" place="margin">Pſal. 65.13.</note> 
               <hi>ſhout and ſing for joy;</hi> is it not Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? What is it that brings your<note n="l" place="margin">Job 5.26. Prov. 3.10.</note> 
               <hi>ſhocks of corn, in their ſeaſons,</hi> into your barns and granaries; is it not Government? By what is it that you are delivered
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:101120:12"/>from Violencies and Plunderings, from Riflings, Rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beries, and Rapine, but alone by this? and (that which is indeed the Diamond ſet in the ring of this whole <hi>Encomium</hi>) by what is your Religion guarded more then by this? all Godlineſſe, as well as Honeſty, is preſerved by this, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.1.2. Remove this, what but ataxyes and diſorders, more deformed then the firſt rude Chaos, break in upon you? as when the Sluces are pulled up, the flouds overflow, not to water, but to waſh away the fruits of the earth: or, as <hi>Heraclitus</hi> once ſaid, If the Sun were wanting, it would ſoon be night, for all the Stars; ſo, where, or when this is abſent,<note n="m" place="margin">Pſal. 137.2.</note> how are the Harpes hung up upon the Willowes? and how do men, as <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtus</hi> ſitting between <hi>Horace</hi> and <hi>Virgil, inter ſuſpiria &amp; lachrymas,</hi> the one given to weeping, and the other to ſighing, ſit down under a night of ſorrow and lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation? I have read of a Law among the <hi>Perſians</hi> to this effect, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, That when their Chief Governour was dead, there ſhould be no Lawes in force, for the ſpace of five dayes together, upon which there enſued ſo Prodigions Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>orders, Violencies and Perturbations, that as ſometime <hi>Rachel</hi> impatient of her barren Womb, cryed out,<note n="n" place="margin">Gen. 30.1.</note> 
               <hi>Give me children or elſe I die;</hi> ſo the people cryed out, O give us Governors to rule, or we die, we are all undone: They had learn'd by the want, to ſet a price upon the enjoyment; as the<note n="*" place="margin">See Pſal. 106 24, 25.</note> pettiſh Iſraelites, (a people ſeldom if ever, pleaſed with Gods preſent Providencies) who<note n="o" place="margin">Exod. 15.24.</note> murmured under <hi>Moſes,</hi> though the<note n="p" place="margin">Numb. 12.3.</note> meekeſt man alive, would yet, in all likelihood, had not God by ſome Angel conveyed his body<note n="q" place="margin">Deut. 34.6.</note> out of ſight,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Vid.</hi> S. Jude ver. 9.</note> (ſo prone were they alſo to Idolatry) have worſhipped him for an Idoll, after he was dead. But I fear that I do all this while, but darken this ſo ſhining a Topaze of Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, by my rude poliſhing; ſith to expreſſe the excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lency thereof, quils pluck'd from the wings of the Bleſſed Seraphims, or Cherubims themſelves, would bee but
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:101120:13"/>competent: Wherefore, waving this humble kind of Oratory; hearken a little, I beſeech you, to what the inſpired<note n="r" place="margin">Amos 3.7.</note> Secretaryes of Heaven it ſelf, the Sacred Pen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the Holy Canon (<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Pet. 1.21.</note> over ruled therein by a Cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtiall direction) have un-erringly, under many Reſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blances, expreſſed of thoſe perſons who manage this great affair, and ſo reflexively the ſplendor of the thing it ſelfe, may be the better diſplayed.</p>
            <p>And out of ſo faire a Garden, adorned with ſo great Variety, I ſhall preſent you with a Poſie of the choiceſt flowers. In the eleventh <hi>Pſalm</hi> and the third verſe, as alſo <hi>Micah</hi> 6.2. they are called metaphorically, <hi>The Foundations of the earth; If the Foundations be deſtroyed, what can the righteous do?</hi> that is, as the moſt Ortho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dox expound it, <hi>Magiſtratus peſſundati,</hi> If Governors, that ſhould be to God's people, as foundations are to the building, ſupports and ſtayes, if theſe are caſt down, that is, either deprived of their Power, or through ſloth or tyranny ſo degenerate from what they ſhould be, that an honeſt man may look for no favour or ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cour from them; then, <hi>what ſhall the righteous do?</hi> Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectly implying, that whileſt they remain as Foundations, unſhaken and<note n="t" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.19.</note> firme, then may the righteous and the true Religion be ſure both of countenance and ſuppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; whence alſo, in a Title of Cognation, they are ſtiled, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 47.9. <hi>The Shields of the earth,</hi> to defend, and to ſafeguard from Injuries and Wrongs.</p>
            <p>In another Style, they are called <hi>Saviours;</hi> ſo is <hi>Oth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niel,</hi> who delivered <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ſtyled, <hi>Judg.</hi> 3.9. We read <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.45. that <hi>Pharaoh</hi> called <hi>Joſeph,</hi> when advanced to the chiefe Government over all <hi>Egypt, Zaphnath Paaneah,</hi> which, in the Hebrew, ſignifieth as much as a revaler of ſecret things, or a myſterious Counſellor, in regard of his Interpretation of <hi>Pharaoh's</hi> Dreame: But, in the <hi>Egyptian</hi> Language, as<note n="u" place="margin">Beauximis in Harmon. Evan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel.</note> 
               <hi>Beauxamis</hi> acquaints us, it is by interpretation, <hi>A Saviour of the world;</hi> in as much as by his Providence, He ſaved ſo many beſides
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:101120:13"/>his Fathers houſe, from periſhing by famine: and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſly: the Magiſtrates, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.27. have the appellation of Saviours, in reſpect of that outward incolumity and ſafety, which they procure to ſuch as are under their Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernance and Protection: To this ſame purpoſe is it, that<note n="*" place="margin">Simon Maio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lus. <hi>p. 347.</hi> de Bellor. Eventu.</note> 
               <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> the Maſter, ſaid to <hi>Alexander</hi> the Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler, Governours were appointed, not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, not, by an Imperious Domination, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come injurious, but, by a gracious Dignation, to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come<note n="x" place="margin">Luke 22.25.</note> Benefactors: So ſaith <hi>Euripides</hi> likewiſe, That a good Magiſtrate was <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; the ſame is alſo ſweetly illuſtrated by that Viſion offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> under the ſimilitude of an high Tree, <hi>Dan.</hi> 4.11, 12. <hi>The leaves whereof were faire, and the fruit thereof much, and in it was meat for all; the Beaſts of the field had ſhadow under it, and the fowls of the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven dwelt in the boughes thereof, and all fleſh was fed of it:</hi> Becauſe the good Magiſtrates procure ſuſtentati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, defence, and quiet Habitation to thoſe that are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der them.</p>
            <p>Again, Under another Metaphor, they are reſembled unto <hi>Paſtors,</hi> or <hi>Shepherds;</hi> So <hi>Cyrus,</hi> whom God un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>expectedly raiſed up for a Deliverer to his people, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 44.28. is called <hi>The Lords Shepherd:</hi> and <hi>Moſes</hi> likens people without a Governour, to ſheep without a Shep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herd, <hi>Numb.</hi> 27.17. And King <hi>David</hi> gives the ſtyle of ſheep unto his Subjects, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 24.17. So in ruling them, he is ſaid to <hi>[feed] Jacob</hi> the Lords <hi>people, and Iſrael his Inheritance,</hi> Pſal. 78.71, 72. So Pſalm 28.9. that word which is tranſlated <hi>[Feed]</hi> thine inheritance, is in the Original <hi>[Rule]</hi> thine inheritance; and that not un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fitly, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith<note n="y" place="margin">Xenophon <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Xenophon,</hi> becauſe the Offices of the one bear a kind of correſpondence with the other, in the ſuppedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation of wholſom paſtures and proviſions: And as it's reported to have been the ſaying of<note n="*" place="margin">Sucton in Tiber.</note> 
               <hi>Tiberius,</hi> 
               <q>It is the care of a good Shepherd <hi>tondêre pecus, non deglu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bere;</hi>
               </q>
               <pb n="20" facs="tcp:101120:14"/>to fleece them, not to flay them: As in the great Charter of <hi>England,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Theodoricus rex admonuit Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellum, Ne plus tribueret Fiſco, quàm Juſtitiae, <hi>Caſſiodor. lib. 1. Epiſt. 22.</hi>
               </note> Fines were impoſed, <hi>ſalvo contenemento,</hi> in a gentle moderation.</p>
            <p>Laſtly, They are called<note n="*" place="margin">Num. 11.12 Exod. 20.12</note> 
               <hi>Fathers,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>: chiefly when good and godly, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49.23. By the Romans, their Senators were called <hi>Patres conſcripti;</hi> and<note n="*" place="margin">Xenoph. l. <hi>8.</hi> 
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>Xe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nophon</hi> approves the Title, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in regard of that providence and nutriti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they have and provide for their people. S.<note n="z" place="margin">S. <hi>Hieron. l.</hi> 9. in Ezek.</note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> obſerves, That, as the King of <hi>Egypt</hi> was ſucceſſively called <hi>Pharaoh,</hi> after one Name; ſo among the Phili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtims, the King was ſtiled <hi>Abimelech,</hi> which is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound, ſignifying <hi>My Father King;</hi> Even as in the other ſex, <hi>Deborah</hi> was ſaid, for counſelling well, to be a <hi>Mother in Iſrael,</hi> Judg. 5.7. <hi>Joſeph,</hi> advanced to the Regiment over <hi>Egypt,</hi> ſaith of himſelf, (<hi>Gen.</hi> 45.8.) That <hi>the Lord had made him a Father to Pharaoh:</hi> and by his command, the people (as he rode in his Chariot of State, <hi>Gen.</hi> 41.43.) were to cry before him, <hi>Abrech,</hi> that is, mild, or tender Father; as<note n="a" place="margin">Hieron. in Tradit. Hebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>icis, ſuper Gen. tom. <hi>3</hi> pag. <hi>390.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hierom</hi> renders it, (from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>&amp;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Pater</hi> &amp; <hi>mollis</hi>) however the LXX take no great notice of the word) before whom all were to how the knee.</p>
            <p>And now, after this ſo copious an amplification, both of the <hi>Office</hi> and <hi>Benefit</hi> of Magiſtracy, or Government, It's time, I preſume, to haſten to an Application of the Point.</p>
            <p>And here (perhaps) it may be expected, on ſome hands,<label type="milestone">
                  <seg type="milestoneunit">Ʋſe. </seg>
               </label> That I ſhould, firſt of all, become a Monitor, at leaſt a Remembrancer to the <hi>Judges</hi> themſelves, and put them in minde of their Duty: But I told you even now, [that] was none of my purpoſe: It were more meet to<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 13.24</note> 
               <hi>beſeech them as</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Num. 11.12 Exod. 20.12</note> 
               <hi>Fathers,</hi> then to inſtruct them as Magiſtrates. I know the <hi>ſnuffers</hi> of the San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary were to be of <hi>pure</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Exod. 37.23</note> 
               <hi>gold;</hi> and I am not of ſo
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:101120:14"/>good metall to take on me to do that; leſt what here <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> inſinuated to his Judges in the plurall, may be returned upon me in the ſingular, <hi>Caveto, Take heed what thou doeſt.</hi> I ſhall therefore become as ſome di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine <hi>Proteus,</hi> to metamorphoſe an expected Exhorta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion into an humble and cordiall Congratulation, to magnifie and bleſſe God, that he hath raiſed up ſo emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Worthies, whoſe Learning in the Lawes, whoſe Sanctity and cleanneſſe of hands will altogether occaſion <hi>judgment to run down as a river, and righteouſneſſe as a mighty ſtream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>My Counſell that I have to ſubminiſter upon this occaſion, muſt look on ſome other objects; at ſuch (I mean) who are under ſuch Magiſtrates; even all ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequious people who are<note n="d" place="margin">Pſal. 35.20</note> 
               <hi>quiet in the Land: Pliny</hi> tels us of ſome herbs, that however they be ſet in the waters, yet will not grow ſo well <hi>abſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> imbribus ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venientibus,</hi> without ſome ſhowers from above: No more will this obedience, which I am now about to preſſe, without continuall watering by good advice.</p>
            <p>And the whole that I have to ſay to ſuch, ſhall be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>duced to theſe four Heads, from whence, as from the<note n="e" place="margin">Gen. 2.10</note> four Rivers in Paradiſe, ſhall be derived ſuch ſtreams as may<note n="f" place="margin">Pſal. 68.9</note> 
               <hi>refreſh the inheritance of God.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Firſt then, Let me minde you of that of the Apoſtle, very appoſite to our preſent purpoſe, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> 
               <hi>Ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to all their dues, Fear to whom fear, Honour to whom honour.</hi> And to whom can there be of right and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience juſtly more due, then to thoſe Higer Powers, who are ordained of God himſelf? It's a <hi>quaere</hi> in Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liticks, Whether a Ruler were better to be feared, or to be loved? <hi>Sigiſmund</hi> the Emperor (as<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Panormitan. de dictis &amp; fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctis Alphonſi,</hi> lib. 4. cap. 35. Vid. Dieter. D<hi rend="sup">n</hi>. 23 poſt Trin. p. 841, 842, &amp;c.</note> 
               <hi>Panormi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tan</hi> acquaints us) wiſely reſolv'd it, That Superiours will be both feared and beloved too: and indeed, both conjoyned argue a reverence meet for Authority. And ſurely, if they be Fathers (as ye heard but now) They muſt have Honour, <hi>Mal.</hi> 1.6. This comes under the
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:101120:15"/>Fifth Commandment, To <hi>honour our Father;</hi> Not one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of our Bodies, but alſo of our Country: And this,
<list>
                  <item>1. In <hi>Thought;</hi> by carrying an awfull and reveren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall eſteem of them, in regard both of their Perſons, and Power; yea, of their Perſons for their Power ſake</item>
                  <item>2. <hi>In Word.</hi> Exod. 22.28. <hi>Thou ſhalt not revile the Gods,</hi> or the Judges, <hi>nor curſe the Rulers of they people, Act.</hi> 23.5. Let us not be too haſty in cenſuring actions of Superiours; for we may ſee but one end of the ſtaffe: like as when a ſtick is put into the water, that part above in the air is ſtreight, though that under the water ſeems crooked, yet is in it ſelf ſtraight ſtill, though we think it otherwiſe. Saint <hi>Peter</hi> makes it a note of ſuch as <hi>Deſpiſe Government,</hi> to be <hi>preſumptuous, ſelf willed,</hi> no way afraid <hi>to [ſpeak evill] of Dignities,</hi> 2 Pet. 2.10. And uſually it holds true, where detraction goes before, as <hi>Eſau;</hi> there ſedition takes, it by the<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 25.26.</note> heel, as <hi>Jacob;</hi> Wherefore (as a<note n="i" place="margin">Biſh. <hi>Andrews</hi> Serm. on <hi>Prov.</hi> 24.21. <hi>p.</hi> 950, 951.</note> Learned man obſerves) the ſame word in the Hebrew, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>[Shonim]</hi> ſignifies both De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tractor, and alſo Seditious; properly, after the Hebrew Criticiſme, they are Biters, it comes of <hi>Shen,</hi> a tooth, they have teeth in their tongues.</item>
                  <item>3. Honour them <hi>in Deed.</hi> Bee ſo far from reſiſting the lawfull Magiſtrate, commanding lawfull things (and good Rulers will be content that men ſhould ſerve God firſt, and them next) that rather, on the other ſide thou ſhouldeſt reſolve to be moulded, as it were Plato<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nically, after all their Legall <hi>Idea's; For they that reſiſt, ſhall receive to themſelves judgement,</hi> Rom. 13.2. Pride this way cannot climb ſo high, but Juſtice will ſit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove it.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> As you muſt give them the Tribute of <hi>Honour,</hi> ſo alſo of your <hi>Prayers,</hi> and <hi>Supplications,</hi> and <hi>Interceſſions,</hi> even for all that are in Authority, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or in Eminent place, <hi>That we may live a quiet and peaceable life, in all godlineſſe and honeſty; for this is good
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:101120:15"/>and acceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour,</hi> 1 Tim. 2.1, 2, 3. So <hi>Jeremy</hi> adviſed the <hi>Jewes,</hi> even under Captivity, to pray for the peace of that place where they were, <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.7. Praying a long Life, wiſe Counſels, ſafe Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, valiant Armies, faithfull People, quiet Times, or whatſoever elſe may conduce to their wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, You muſt give them the Tribute of <hi>Obedience</hi> and due <hi>Homage,</hi>
               <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> (they giving you protection) in what they command, according to God, and according to Juſt and good Laws (for otherwiſe we muſt chuſe <hi>rather to obey God, then man</hi> againſt God, <hi>Act.</hi> 5.29. after the example of<note n="k" place="margin">Eſth. 3.2.</note> 
               <hi>Mordecai,</hi> and of the three Children, <hi>Dan.</hi> 3.8.) So the Apoſtle <hi>Paul, Rom.</hi> 13.1. Let every ſoul be ſubject, even for conſcience of Gods Ordinance, and that, not <hi>Timore paenae, ſed amore Juſtitiae,</hi> as S.<note n="l" place="margin">
                  <hi>Gregor.</hi> Mag. l. <hi>35.</hi> c. <hi>10.</hi> Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſ. Moral.</note> 
               <hi>Grego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> expounds it, Not for the ſervile fear of puniſhment, but out of the charitative love of Juſtice. To the ſame purpoſe S. <hi>Peter</hi> in that famous Text, 1 Pet. 2.13, 14. and again S. <hi>Paul, Tit.</hi> 3.1. <hi>Put them in mind to be ſubject to Principalities and Powers, to obey Magiſtrates:</hi> This will be a mean to keep a City or a Common Wealth in Peace and Safety, if, as ſometimes that wiſe Lawgiver <hi>Solon,</hi> in<note n="m" place="margin">Stobaeus <hi>c.</hi> 43 <hi>De Republ. p.</hi> 280.</note> 
               <hi>Stobaeus,</hi> ſaid, <hi>Cives obtemperent ſuis Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratibus, Magiſtratus autem legibus;</hi> The Citizens obey the Magiſtrate, and the Magiſtrate the Lawes.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, and laſtly,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> There muſt be given them <hi>Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute</hi> and <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> all ſubſidiary Supplies, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.7. due to them for all their publick care, Providence, Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, Vigilancy, great Travell and Pains, which they undertake and undergo for the generall good of commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity. There is an old word made uſe of by ſome for money, in Latine, <hi>Moneta, à Monendo,</hi> ſo called (ſaith<note n="n" place="margin">Dieter. <hi>quâ ſupra, p</hi> 849.</note> one) from moniſhing men of their duty, due even by it to the publick Magiſtrate; ſome there be who love to deſire the Magiſtrate, but they do not deſire to love the Magiſtrate; they care not how much the Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrate
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:101120:16"/>doth for them, but they regard not how little they do for Him. Even our Saviour Himſelf with his parents ſubmitted to the Tax of <hi>Auguſtus Caeſar,</hi> who then ſway<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the Empire, when he was born, <hi>Luke</hi> 2.4, 5. and af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards provided both for himſelf and <hi>Peter</hi> (to avoid offence) a piece of Tribute Money, <hi>Matth.</hi> 17.27. Now it is not the meaneſt part of Religion to imitate him, whom thou worſhippeſt in things capable of i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitation.</p>
            <p>I ſhall not need many<note n="o" place="margin">Eccleſ. 12.11</note> nayles to faſten this perſwaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on upon you; ſith the conſideration of the greatneſſe, not of the dignity, more then of the weight and burden of the office it ſelf, is enough: This appears by the ſame Title which <hi>Jethro</hi> gave it, when he counſelled <hi>Moſes</hi> to joyn Aſſiſtants with him, to help to bear the [<note n="*" place="margin">Num. 11.11</note> 
               <hi>Burden</hi>] of Judicature with him, <hi>Exod.</hi> 18.22. this <hi>Honos</hi> is alſo <hi>Onus:</hi> the Naturaliſts obſerve, that the head is leaner then any part of the body, becauſe it takes care for all: The Governours empty themſelves as it were of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, to beſtow themſelves on the Publick; yea, if they care for themſelves at all, they do it more for the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples ſake, then for their own, as if they thought them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves only ordeined for their weal, often breaking their owne reſt, that they may the better procure yours.</p>
            <q>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>,<note place="margin">Homer.</note>
               </l>
               <l>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</l>
            </q>
            <p>Briefly, without uſing more arguments, I well read in the hilarity of your looks, the alacrity of your hearts,
<q>
                  <l>—Super omnia vultus</l>
                  <l>Acceſſêre boni.—</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>I diſcover your readineſſe to cloſe with me in this ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious intimation. Give me leave then to interrogate and return anſwer to my ſelfe, as ſometimes<note n="p" place="margin">Act. 26.27.</note> 
               <hi>Paul</hi> did on another occaſion of <hi>Agrippa, King Agrippa, Beleeveſt thou the Prophets? I know that thou beleeveſt:</hi> So, my Beloved and Chriſtian Hearers, do you, as <hi>Jeremy</hi> hath
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:101120:16"/>expreſſed it, <hi>cap.</hi> 30.21. do you <hi>[engage]</hi> your hearts to approach unto the Lord? I, as S. <hi>Paul,</hi> or as the<note n="q" place="margin">Judg. 5, 29.</note> mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of <hi>Siſera,</hi> may return anſwer to my ſelf, I know that you do engage your hearts to approach unto the Lord; and withall to a willing ſubjection to thoſe High<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Powers of Magiſtracy, the great advantage and bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit whereof you have thus far heard enlarged: Yea, as S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaid of <hi>Philemons</hi> readineſſe to give entertainment to <hi>Oneſimus</hi> upon his motion, I know that you will do<note n="r" place="margin">Philem. v. 21.</note> more then I ſay; being, as the ſame Apoſtle ſaid of <hi>Titus,</hi> in relation to another Exhortation, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.17. more forward of your own accord: And indeed, how can it be otherwiſe with you? if, in the next place, you ſeriouſly conſider the Commiſſion, or Divine Authority of this Office, which we have here preſented to us in the ſecond member of my Diviſion; contained under theſe words, <hi>Ye judge not for man, but for the Lord: Vices Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mini gerentes, as Junius</hi> gloſſeth it, as Gods Vice-gerents, doing his buſineſſe, and executing what he himſelf com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands.</p>
            <p>Which now comes in order to be fully, but ſuccinctly ſpoken of; on which I ſhall ſo ſtrive to husband my Diſcourſe, as to lay it out in a due proportion to the time. <hi>And he ſaid to the Judges, Take heed what ye do, for ye judge not for man, but for the Lord.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Ordination of theſe Powers is<note n="ſ" place="margin">Vide <hi>Calvin.</hi> Inſtit. l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>20.</hi> Pertot. &amp; S. <hi>Auguſt.</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> c. <hi>33.</hi> De Civ. Dci.</note> divine,<note place="margin">The 2<hi rend="sup">d</hi> Part</note> they are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Ordained of God himſelf,</hi> ſaith the great Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.1. By me, that is, by my own Paramount Authority, ſaith the Lord, rule even all the Judges of the earth, <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.16. <hi>[Per] me,</hi> [By] me, The nature of this Praepoſition is to note a Cauſe certain, and a certain Cauſe excludeth Chance; they be no Caſualties, <hi>Fortè fortunâ,</hi> at hap hazard, Cauſalls they are, (ſaid<note n="t" place="margin">Biſh. <hi>Andrews</hi> Serm. on <hi>Prov.</hi> 8.15 <hi>p.</hi> 935.</note> one, ſometimes a great Ornament of this Church:) Caſual they are not: <hi>Per me,</hi> not <hi>Perſe:</hi> it's worth the noting, that it is ſaid, By me, not by, or
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:101120:17"/>from themſelves; it is not their own place they ſit in, nor their own Power they execute, it is derived to them from God himſelf; ſo that they may ſay of themſelves even in this regard, <hi>Ipſe nos fecit, non ipſi nos, It is he that hath made us,</hi>
               <note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 100.3.</note> 
               <hi>and not we our ſelves;</hi> and therefore the Judgement that they decree is Gods, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17. <hi>Many ſeek the Rulers favour</hi> (ſaith <hi>Solomon</hi>) <hi>but every mans Judgement cometh from the Lord,</hi> Prov. 29.26. And indeed, as <hi>Joſephus</hi> expreſſeth it, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Without God it is utterly im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible that any ſuch Power ſhould ſubſiſt in the world; conſidering the furious, and ſeditious Commotions that Satan the Author of Confuſion and Rebellion, is apt to raiſe up in the breſts, to vent and foment in and by the actions of the ſons of <hi>Belial,</hi> againſt all Authority of Divine appointment. But it is<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 144.2.</note> God who ſubdueth one man in ſubjection to the other, for the more uniforme Compoſure, and Peace of the whole Univerſe: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore when men offer to reject that forme of Government which is by providence caſt upon them, in the language and ſtyle of the Holy Ghoſt, they do not reject man, but they do reject God himſelf, that he ſhould not rule over them, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 8.7.</p>
            <p>For this cauſe is it, that God himſelfe (whoſe Vice<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerents they are upon earth) to grace, and honour their perſons, and Authority the more, hath given them the Title of his own name, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.6. <hi>I have ſaid, ye are</hi>
               <note n="x" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gods:</hi> and again, <hi>Exod.</hi> 22.28. which are not <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Swelling words of vanity,</hi> titles of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plement, or of Adulation, but they are of Gods Royall impoſition. Nor is this Old Teſtament onely, as ſome would have it, but our Bleſſed Saviour in the New Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament, comments upon theſe very ſame words, <hi>Joh.</hi> 10.34, 35. where, not only the Title, but the word, that is, the Warrant and Commiſſion they receive from God is as a binding Law, which cannot be looſed. Now ſo they are called, ſay<note n="y" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Aug. Tract.</hi> 48. <hi>in</hi> John. and <hi>Lyra in</hi> Pſal. 82.</note> 
               <hi>Auſtin</hi> and <hi>Lyra,</hi> by participation,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:101120:17"/>
               <hi>Participando fiunt dii, tanquam lumina illuminata,</hi> in regard of their derivative power, as lights enlight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned from on high: They are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>called Gods,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 8.5. in reſpect of their deputed power from God; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith<note n="z" place="margin">Juſt. Mart. qu. ad Orthod. <hi>142.</hi> Confer. <hi>B. King</hi> pag <hi>166 on Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nah.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Justin Martin,</hi> that Uſe, or Office ceaſing, the Title leaves them: For however they be Gods with men, yet are they but men with God, who <hi>ſtandeth in the Congregation of</hi> thoſe <hi>Gods, Pſal.</hi> 82. <hi>ver.</hi> 1. and that, not onely as a ſpectator to behold them, which noteth his <hi>preſence;</hi> but alſo as a Judge above them, which notes his <hi>preheminence;</hi> intending one day to take an account both of them and all their proceedings, which under his Title, and by his Autho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity they undertook.</p>
            <p>Now Gods own proceeding in Judicature is preſented to us in the glaſſe of the Scriptures, after this manner.</p>
            <p>Firſt, It's Impartiall, and without reſpect of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons: ſo here, <hi>ver.</hi> 7. <hi>There is no iniquity with the Lord our God</hi> (ſaith <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi>) <hi>nor reſpect of perſons;</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, as the <hi>Septuagint</hi> ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it. So they who judg for God, though they may have reſpect to the equity of the Cauſe; yet may not have of the quality of the<note n="*" place="margin">Deut. 16.19.</note> perſon, above the Cauſe. <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17. <hi>the face of the poor man becauſe hee is poor,</hi> muſt not be <hi>regarded;</hi> nor rich mens perſons held <hi>in admiration,</hi> as Saint<note n="a" place="margin">Jude v. 16.</note> 
               <hi>Jude</hi> ſpeaks, for any advantage whatſoever: As was ſaid of <hi>Anacharſis</hi> Laws, they were like Spiders webs, which the bigger flies brake through, but the leſſer were taken and held faſt therein: but as <hi>Phocylides</hi> hath it,
<q>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.</q> Do judgment, not for<note n="*" place="margin">Vid. Epiſc. <hi>Davenant. pag.</hi> 966. <hi>Expoſ. in</hi> Coloſſ.</note> Favour, but for Juſtice ſake. The Ancients (as we read in Scripture) held their Judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catories in the<note n="b" place="margin">Ruth. 4.1. &amp; Gen. 34.20. Prov. 31.23.</note> 
               <hi>gates of their Cities,</hi> for the more free and open acceſſe of all, as well ſmall as great: <hi>Juſtitia non novit Patrem, non novit Matrem, Veritatem novit,</hi>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:101120:18"/>ſaith<note n="c" place="margin">Dieter. D<hi rend="sup">n</hi>. 23 poſt Trin. pag. 840.</note> one; A Magiſtrate on the Bench ſhould be like <hi>Melchizedek, without father, without mother,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>without</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Hebr. 7.3</note> 
               <hi>deſcent, or kindred.</hi> As I have heardit reported of a<note n="*" place="margin">Judg <hi>Pop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham.</hi>
               </note> Judg (ſometime of this Weſtern Circuit) when one arraigned before him, alledged, that he was his kinſman, however then an offender before him (as there are but few Families wherein ſome (as the grains in the faireſt Pomegranate) are not tainted; and as it is in the hebrew proverb, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Vinegar may be the ſon of Wine</hi>) Are you ſo, ſaid He? I muſt therefore never the later condemn you, being convicted; I muſt deny my ſelf, with all my relations, to make Juſtice exemplary. A Judge muſt be (to uſe the word of<note n="c" place="margin">Aul. Gel. noct. Attic. l. <hi>14.</hi> c. <hi>4</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Gellius</hi>) <hi>Inadu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>labilis,</hi> above flattery; or as<note n="f" place="margin">Cic. l. <hi>1.</hi> Tuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul. queſt.</note> 
               <hi>Tully</hi> expreſſeth it, <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>exorabilis,</hi> beyond intreaty, when the Cauſe expects it. <hi>Plutarch</hi> in the life of <hi>Themiſtocles,</hi> reports of him, That when <hi>Simonides</hi> the Poet of <hi>Chios</hi> deſired a favour of him, beſide what was juſt and equall, made anſwer, As thou ſhouldeſt be but an ill Poet, if thou ſhouldeſt not obſerve Numbers, and due Meaſures in thine Art; So neither can I be a good Praetor, in caſe I doe prefer any mans favour before the equity of the Laws.</p>
            <p n="2">2. And yet ſecondly, although God be impartiall, in reſpect of the Perſon; yet is he full of equanimity in reſpect of the execution of his Judgment, even after con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viction: <hi>In the</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Hab. 3.2</note> 
               <hi>midſt of judgment God remembers mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy;</hi> nor without incorrigible provocations doth he <hi>exe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cute the fierceneſſe of his anger, Hoſ.</hi> 11.9. Yea, though Juſtice and mercy are Attributes both equally in God; yet <hi>quoad nos,</hi> in reſpect of us, the manifeſtation of the acts of clemency ſeem to come more kindly from him, then thoſe of ſeverity: The acts of mercy flow from God (the<note n="g" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.3</note> 
               <hi>Father of mercies</hi>) as a ſtream running kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, and derived clearly from a ſweet Spring or Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine: but the acts of Juſtice, like liquor, or wine from the grape, which is not without ſqueezing or<note n="h" place="margin">Gen. 40.11</note> preſſing forth: From God floweth not more Mercy then Juſtice;
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:101120:18"/>yet <hi>[rather]</hi> Mercy then Juſtice: And therefore when he proceeds to <hi>wrath,</hi> he is ſaid by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.21. <hi>to doe his work, a [ſtrange] work;</hi> as if he had been unacquainted with ſuch an act: It is obſerved, That God was longer in deſtroying one poor City <hi>Jericho,</hi> then he was in making the whole world;<note n="i" place="margin">Joſh. 6.16.</note> for he was [ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven] days in deſtroying it, but<note n="k" place="margin">Gen. 1.31. Exod. 20 11</note> ſix dayes only in crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the world; In the ſecond Commandment we read of his viſitation of wrath but unto the third and fourth Generation of them that hated him, but of his mercy unto [<note n="l" place="margin">Exod. 20.6.</note> 
               <hi>Thouſands</hi>] of them that love him. Its worth our Obſervation alſo, how our Saviour wrought no de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive miracles, but all ſalving, or reſtorative: Wee read in the Goſpel, that our Saviour was once angry, but it was in an anger of Zeal, not of Livor, when he ſaw his Fathers Houſe (the Houſe of Prayer) to become, by buying and ſelling therein, a Den of Theeves, rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bing God of his due honour in that place; he then made a<note n="m" place="margin">Joh. 2.15.</note> Whip of ſmall cords to ſcourge thoſe Money-Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers out of the Temple; he made a <hi>whip,</hi> to ſhew his diſpleaſure, but of [ſmall] cords, to ſhew the mitigati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of that diſpleaſure; God ſends his lightning with<note n="n" place="margin">Pſal. 135.7.</note> rain, ſaith the Pſalmiſt; as the one affrights with fiery flaſhes, and coruſcations, ſo the other cooles, and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forts the inflamed ayre; yea, tis obſerved by<note n="o" place="margin">Ruffin. <hi>Hiſt. l.</hi> 2 <hi>c.</hi> 23.</note> 
               <hi>Ruffinus</hi> in his Story, that the Ancients were wont to place upon the Statue of their Jupiter, <hi>Modium,</hi> a certain meaſure, as an embleme of Moderation: And this by way of Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logy, is imitated by thoſe who are called Gods with men. Clemency is that golden thread, which runs through all their actions of Judicature: They will remember that of<note n="p" place="margin">
                  <hi>Chryſoſt.</hi> Ser. De Manſuetud.</note> 
               <hi>Chryſoſtome.</hi> That its better to give account to God the<note n="q" place="margin">Heb. 12.23.</note> Judge of all, for ſhewing mercy, rather then too much rigour or ſeverity; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith<note n="r" place="margin">Iſidor. Peluſiot. l. <hi>3</hi> cpiſt. <hi>131.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iſidor Peluſiota,</hi> Extremeties prove often dangerous; There is more ſafety in walking in the mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle path, then upon the very brink of the River; if
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:101120:19"/>men do all they may do, they may ſoon bee apt to do (through humane Infirmities or Paſſions) what they ſhould not do; Moderation therefore, and a ſweet<note n="ſ" place="margin">2 Cor. 10.1.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> (ſith the Law Maxime is, <hi>Juſtitia neſcit iraſci</hi>) may be like that water obſerved by Anatomiſts in the <hi>Pericardium,</hi> which cooles the <hi>Ebullitions</hi> about the heart; or like <hi>Minerva</hi>'s golden bridle to the winged horſe: it makes a good Magiſtrate alwaies to carry a Chancery in his own breſt, and inclines him, like the Maſter Bee, to rule, but without a ſting. And yet, let me not be miſtaken neither, for it is ſo ſometimes, that <hi>Summa juſtitia</hi> proves to be <hi>Summa miſericordia,</hi> the extremity of Juſtice, the height of Mercy; it is, when Juſtice is executed upon obſtinate Malefactors, then mercy is ſhewen to the Country, which they ſpoil, tifle and depopulate. <hi>Bonis Nocet, quiſquis pepercerit malis,</hi> ſaith<note n="t" place="margin">Seneca, ſen. <hi>99.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Seneca:</hi> he hurts the Innocent, who ſpares the Nocent: In this caſe Juſtice deals like <hi>Alcon,</hi> who eſpying a Dragon to claſp his child, ſo directed his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row, that he ſhot the Dragon, and preſerved the child. In cutting off unreclaimable Malefactors, Vice is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed, Vertue encouraged, and the Country preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved: It was the ſaying of <hi>Ludovicus Divus,</hi> as is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in the Annalls of <hi>France, Pietatis opus eſt, non ſaevi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiae, juſtitiam facere.</hi> It was an act of Piety, and not of cruelty to do Juſtice; ſo that, this notwithſtanding, Mercy like a refulgent beam of the orient Sun, may ſhine in the midſt of Judgement from the Seat of an upright Magiſtrate.</p>
            <p n="3">3.<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Saith <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi> here, With the Lord our God there is no taking of gifts; yea, covetouſneſſe is as<note n="u" place="margin">Col 3.5.</note> Idolatry; and God<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 10.8.</note> abhorrs both it, and the perſons that bow down to it; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; ſaith<note n="x" place="margin">Iſidor Peluſiot. l. <hi>3.</hi> Epiſt. <hi>337.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Iſidor Peluſiota;</hi> 'tis for Vultures, not for Eagles, to prey upon garbadge: Magiſtrates, like the <hi>woman cloathed with the Sun, Rev.</hi> 12.1. that is, the Church arrayed in the robes
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:101120:19"/>of the Lord Chriſt, <hi>the Sun of Righteouſneſs</hi> (as he is ſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.2.) they have the Moon under their feet, by which fickle and dim Star, all the inconſtant vanities of this Sublunary lower world (where, with many, the preſent Poſſeſſion is but the Poſſeſſion of the preſent) are reſembled. Oh what a pure breſt, and what cleane hands had innocent <hi>Samuel</hi> (a Prophet, and withall a Judge too in <hi>Iſrael</hi>) when bidding his laſt adieu to the world, and putting off his Office with his earthly Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacle, he made a challenge to all, ſaying, <hi>Whoſe Ox have I</hi>
               <note n="y" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.3.4</note> 
               <hi>taken, or whoſe Aſſe</hi> (he means unjuſtly) <hi>or whom have I defrauded?</hi> and the people anſwer him, as every<note n="*" place="margin">2 Sam. 23 3, 4</note> juſt Rulers conſcience ſhould to him, <hi>Thou haſt not defrauded:</hi> O the tranquility of a ſpotleſſe breſt! there is nothing to a man in Judicature comparable to <hi>Samuels</hi> integrity, both to get, and to keep an inward, ſolid peace: Who then would ſuffer his eyes by<note n="*" place="margin">See Exod. 23.8. Deut. 16.19 Eccleſ. 7.7.</note> bribe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry or corruption, to be blinded, as old <hi>Tobits</hi> were, with the Swallows dung of this earth; or end anger the whole ſhip of his ſoul for a little ballaſt of gain?<note n="z" place="margin">1 Sam. 12.3.</note> 
               <note n="*" place="margin">Tob. 2.10.</note> Its ſaid among the Poets, that the River<note n="a" place="margin">Sic tibi cum fluctus ſubterla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bêre Sicanos, Doris amara ſuam non inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſceat undam. <hi>Virgi.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Alpheus</hi> glides under the ſalt ſea, yet ſtill preſerves it ſelf untainted by the brack<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iſh waters, till it ſalutes the ſweet and limpid Fountaine <hi>Arethuſa;</hi> ſo all Godly and Religious Governors keep themſelves (<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>. Ho. mer.</note> above others) unſpotted<note n="b" place="margin">Jam 1.27.</note> of the world, till they drink of the well of Life in the new <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> I mean, till their ſouls be refreſhed with pure comfort in the Kingdome of Heaven.</p>
            <p>And yet, perchance, though the Prophet will not be tempted, 'tis not impoſſible, but there may bee ſome<note n="c" place="margin">2 King. 5.20.</note> 
               <hi>Gehazi,</hi> whom ſome ſhekels of Silver, or ſome chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ges of Rayment, may, though to the hazard of a Le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proſie to be entailed upon Poſterity, ſecretly ſeduce: But becauſe I know none ſuch in this Circuit to be taint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed (and who can take a fixed aim at a flying mark?) yet however I know men may be<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 6.1.</note> tempted, as <hi>Atalanta</hi> was ſtopped in the way by the Golden Apples: Wherefore
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:101120:20"/>let me not be miſtaken; thus think, My Speech is no Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proof which ſuppoſeth a Crime, but only as a Caution to foreſtall ſuch Temptations, that like the ſons of <hi>Zer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viah</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> may in ſome particulars, prove [<note n="e" place="margin">Sam. 3.39.</note> too hard] for them.</p>
            <p>And ſo I come to the fourth and laſt Particular,<milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> that I ſhall at this time make any inſtance in: <hi>Gods Judgement is not paſſed without deliberation precedent:</hi> Hence its ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervable, That before ſentence paſſed upon <hi>Adam</hi> the <hi>Protoplaſt,</hi> and the very firſt man that ſinned, God came to him, not in the heat of any ſubitaneous Paſſion, but <hi>in the</hi>
               <note n="f" place="margin">Gen. 3.8, 9.</note> 
               <hi>cool of the day,</hi> and then reaſoned with him, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Adam, Where art thou? Non in quo loco, quaero, ſed in quo ſtatu,</hi> as S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> upon that Paſſage; I do not ask, Where thou art in reſpect of Place, but where thou art, in reſpect of Grace? Firſt Convincing, before he Doomed him: So likewiſe read we, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 1.18. that though the ſins of <hi>Iſrael</hi> were (in guilt) as red as Crim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon or Scarlet, that by their very hue called for a Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of the ſame colour, as appears <hi>ver.</hi> 20. yet before the ſword was actually unſheathed, <hi>Come,</hi> ſaith the Lord, <hi>and let is: [reaſon] together,</hi> and debate the matter: In like ſort, by proportion and Analogy are the proceedings of theſe terreſtiall Gods with men; and indeed, ſo much is implyed in <hi>Jehoſhaphats Cavete</hi> here, <hi>Take heed what ye do, Ne praecipitantèr, ſed cum magnâ deliberatione ſenten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiam feratis,</hi> ſaith <hi>Lyra:</hi> Be not over haſty in Judgement. Your Commiſſions run (as I ſuppoſe) with <hi>Oyer</hi> before <hi>Terminer,</hi> Hear, before you determine.<note n="g" place="margin">
                  <hi>Eraſmus</hi> l. <hi>4.</hi> Apotheg. A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lexand. <hi>46.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Eraſmus,</hi> among the Apothegmes that he collected of <hi>Alexander</hi> the Great, notes this as a principall, He ſhould alwayes reſerve one ear open to the Defendant, as he hath given the other to the Plaintiff; for elſe, praepoſſeſſion may prove a prejudice;<note n="h" place="margin">Prov. 18.17.</note> 
               <hi>He that is firſt in his own cauſe,</hi> ſaith <hi>Solo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon,</hi> though really moſt obnoxious, yet often apparent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly makes his matter moſt ſpecious, and feaſible: Surely, ſome Cauſes are very difficult, and hard, <hi>Deut.</hi> 1.17. So
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:101120:20"/>that, as <hi>Agapetus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Juſtinian,</hi> He needed to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and to have many eyes aſſiſted by Cauti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Circumſpection; like thoſe living Creatures which S. <hi>Gregory</hi> mentions, which were <hi>in circuitu,</hi>
               <note n="i" place="margin">
                  <hi>S. Oregor.</hi> Mag. par. <hi>3.</hi> Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtor. Cur. Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon. <hi>5.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>&amp; intus oculis plena,</hi> full of eyes within and without, well eying the ſubſtance of the Cauſe within, and obſerving all the circumſtances of it round about; it may other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe prove difficult to keep the Balance even, and juſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to decide it. I have read of a Spaniſh Judge, when a murther was committed in a tumultuous crowd of people, he cauſed all their boſomes to be made bare, and ſo feeling upon their breſts, diſcovered the guilty author by the palpitation and panting of his heart; ſo will a prudent Magiſtrate by ſharpneſs and acuity of un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding, upon debate, ſo anatomize the very bow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>els of a Cauſe, that a fair outſide only, by vertue of ſome gawdy dreſſe, may not carry the matter: <hi>He that ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth therefore</hi> (ſaith the great Apoſtle) <hi>let him do it</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>with diligence,</hi> Rom. 12.8.</p>
            <p>And thus I have done with my Analogies: Now, as the Apoſtle to the<note n="k" place="margin">Heb. 13.22.</note> 
               <hi>Hebrews,</hi> ſuffer, I beſeech you, a word of Exhortation; I cannot tune it to a better Harp, then to that of the ſweet Singer of <hi>Iſrael, Pſal.</hi> 2.10.11. <hi>Be learned ye Judges of the earth, ſerve the Lord with fear.</hi> Now, Judges ſerve God two manner of wayes, 1. As <hi>men;</hi> by<note n="l" place="margin">Pſal. 50.23.</note> ordering their converſation aright, according to the Lawes of the Lord. 2. And<note n="m" place="margin">S. Auguſt <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt.</hi> 50. <hi>ad Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifac.</hi>
               </note> as <hi>Judges,</hi> in <hi>quantum</hi> Judges, when they do thoſe things in, and for the ſervice of the Lord, which none can do but Judges, by vertue of their Office and Commiſſion, which is to execute Juſtice and Judgement, according to the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous Lawes of the Land; and being in a right ſenſe <hi>Cuſtodes utriuſque Tabulae,</hi> to have the firſt regard to what concerns the right Religion, and the next to the ſupportation of equability amongſt men: ſo ſhall they ſhew themſelves what they are by Divine Ordination, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Rom.</hi> 13.4. <hi>The Miniſters of
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:101120:21"/>God for good</hi> to the Common Wealth: ſo ſhall they be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Living Lawes.</hi> In ſhort, becauſe I muſt haſten (as well knowing this to be none of <hi>Jeſhuah</hi>'s dayes, wherein the Sun<note n="n" place="margin">Joſh. 10.13.</note> ſtood ſtill) There is not in the world a more reaſonable requeſt then this, namely; What you [would] be, that [to] be, to make good your name, to be as Gods to men, in doing good; for God (for whom ye Judge) is good, and<note n="o" place="margin">Pſal. 119 68.</note> doth good; ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially the common good to all: for ſo doth God do, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 145.9. this is the time and place for it; and ſo my wiſh is, that they may, and my truſt is, that they will do. Nor have I in all theſe intimations, done other, then ſhewen them a mirror of what they are already; as not needing, nor indeed preſuming to exhort them farther to what they ſhould be: Themſelves will take notice of <hi>Jehoſhaphat</hi>'s doubled <hi>Cavete</hi> in the Text; ſith they judge not for man, that is, as ſome interpret, they may not pleaſe any man in his ſin, nor may they ſin (in<note n="*" place="margin">Prov. 18.5.</note> Judgment) to pleaſe any man: But they judge for God, and for his glory; who, upon ſo doing, is with them in the Judgement; With them as a Spectator, which notes his preſence; With them as a Mighty Protector, which notes his Preheminence; God is thus with them, thus judging; Wherefore now, if ever, <hi>Let the fear of the Lord be upon them, take heed, and do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And thus, after my meaſure, as I could, though not after my wiſhes, as I would (in a meet correſpondence to ſuch an Auditory), I have diſpatched my main inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions for this time. There are yet more parts of my firſt Diviſion remaining; but the time and the weighty affairs enſuing command me to diſmiſſe the larger hand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thoſe at the preſent.</p>
            <p>I ſhall humbly crave the favour only to preſſe even with a Laconical brevity, this Exhortation of <hi>Jehoſhaphat,</hi> in the cloſe of the Text, in a latitude, or larger extenſion unto all in generall: and I ſhall only, as <hi>Jonathan</hi> did the Honey, touch all but as with the<note n="p" place="margin">1 Sam. 14.27.</note> tip of my ſtaffe,
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:101120:21"/>or dip in it the end of my rod; and may the ſame hand that gave this opportunity, add alſo a ſucceſſe to this buſineſſe. Now, <hi>Let the fear of the Lord bee upon you all.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>An Exhortation, though at all times uſefull, yet at this time very opportune, and ſeaſonable; ſith we are fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>len into thoſe laſt dayes of which the Prophecy was, That in them<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 24.12.</note> 
               <hi>Iniquity ſhould abound;</hi> and wherein the wounds of the Church ſeem ſo wide, that none but Heavens Chyrurgery can cure them; and if it ſhould be ſaid now to me, what the Lord did ſometime to the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet, Son of man, <hi>What</hi>
               <note n="r" place="margin">Jer. 1.11.</note> 
               <hi>ſeeſt thou?</hi> Surely, I muſt return anſwer (which I do alſo, <hi>Non exclamantis ſtudio,</hi> but <hi>dolentis affectu;</hi> not out of a deſire to declaim on the diſmembred condition of theſe broken times, but only to declare my zealous ſorrow for them) I ſay, I muſt re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne anſwer, I ſee a world of Atheiſme and Ungodli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe in moſt ſorts of men to ſuperabound; Sin, with more ſpots then the<note n="ſ" place="margin">Jer. 13.23.</note> Leopard hath upon him, in all kind of variety, flowes to the height of full ſea, whileſt puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of Religion, and manners, keeps for the moſt part, at a low water mark; ſo little, or no<note n="t" place="margin">Rom. 3.18.</note> fear of God is there upon earth, or<note n="u" place="margin">Luke 18.2.</note> reverence of good men: and from this great depravation in maners, proceeds ſo great corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in Judgement; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the<note n="*" place="margin">Ariſtot. <hi>Eth. l</hi> 6. <hi>c.</hi> 5.</note> Arch Philoſopher, Wickedneſſe in practice corrupts e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the very principles of reaſon, and of Religion both; as, on the other ſide, a<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 111.10.</note> right underſtanding, and the<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 25.14. and Prov. 3.32.</note> ſecret of the Lord, is with them that fear him: we find that that ſame <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Reprobate, and in-judi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cious mind ariſeth from vile affections, and from an un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeemly converſation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1.24, 28. Hence ſpring thoſe monſters of opinion vented in ſpeeches, and in Pam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phlets, whereby many have taken pains (the more is the pity) to deſtroy thoſe principall ſpurs and motives un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to all Vertue, to wit, the providence of God, the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the dead, the immortality of the ſoul, the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:101120:22"/>Joyes of a future Locall Heaven, and the pains of a fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Locall Hell, the Radicall cauſe (ſaith Learned<note n="z" place="margin">
                  <hi>Hooker</hi> Eccl. Polit. l. <hi>5.</hi> p. <hi>188</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hooker</hi>) of their Atheiſme, and the miſerable<note n="a" place="margin">See Biſh. <hi>King</hi> upon <hi>Jon. p.</hi> 62. <hi>&amp;</hi> 275.</note> ſcandall of the Chriſtian Religion: O take heed what ye do, and (if there be any here within this audience, this day, who ſecretly harbour ſuch thoughts bordering upon blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemy) O ſerve the Lord with fear, and with trembling; For this let me tell all ſuch, without fear of their faces, or bluſhing in mine own, whether they will hear, or whether they will<note n="b" place="margin">Ezek. 2.5.</note> forbear; either they ſhall ſerve to the building, if their hearts be ſound or ſtreight; or if hollow and crooked, to the burning: ſerve they muſt all, one way or other.</p>
            <p>But I am, thus, too generall; I now come in order to make a more particular Application, according to this occaſion. I have<note n="c" place="margin">Vid. <hi>Joh. Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rard.</hi> loc. Com. tom. <hi>6.</hi> p. <hi>447. §. 7.</hi> De Magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtratu Polit.</note> read, that of old, men were wont to build their Villages nigh to ſome one common Fountain, which in the Greek tongue is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, and in the Dorick Dialect thereof, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, from whence all of the Vicinity were denominated <hi>Pagani,</hi> living in open buildings with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any wall to compaſſe them; and yet all that water in that common Fountain, could not advantage any, unleſſe every one for himſelf had brought thither his own Pitcher, and had drawn up, and drank it for his own particular refreſhing: In like manner, I ſhall now ſtrive to<note n="d" place="margin">2 Tim. 2.15.</note> divide to every one his proper<note n="*" place="margin">Luke 12.42</note> porti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p>And firſt of all,<note place="margin">Advice to M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. High Sheriffe, M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                  <hi>John Trot</hi> Eſquire, of <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſtoke.</hi>
               </note> I ſhall crave leave to preſent my de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires to Mr. High Sheriff, whoſe merits (being ſo tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendent as they are) have betimes won him the regards and high Reputation of this Country, and whoſe fideli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty inclined the State to promote him to this preſent Sta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: I ſhall requeſt him to be but like himſelf (for as <hi>Juno</hi> ſaid of <hi>Hercules</hi> in <hi>Seneca, Quaeris Alcidae parem? Nemo eſt niſi ipſe;</hi> If he will contend with an equall, he muſt ſtrive with himſelf): I ſhall beſeech him but to do as he doth do, ſo piouſly, ſo prudently, ſo munificently,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:101120:22"/>and he ſhall ſtop the mouth of all contradiction; yea, his name and praiſe is already mounted upon the wings of honour, and carryed throughout his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey.</p>
            <p>Next,<note place="margin">Advice to the Grand Jury.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed what ye do,</hi> and <hi>Let the fear of the Lord be upon you</hi> alſo, Gentlemen of the Grand Inqueſt; Your Wiſedome and Providence, like to a well drawn Picture, muſt look upon every corner of your Countrey: God, by you, makes<note n="e" place="margin">Pſal. 9.12.</note> Inquiſition for Blood, that it may be cleanſed; for Sabbath-Breakers, that they may be avenged; for Blaſphemers of Gods Name, or Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances; for when you are tender of God's<note n="f" place="margin">1 Sam. 2.30.</note> Honour, God will be of your ſafety: For Antichriſtian Popery, and Superſtitious Idolatry, that it may be purged; for Jeſuiticall Impoſtors, thoſe who carry Jeſus in their Names, but<note n="g" place="margin">Rev. 9.11.</note> 
               <hi>Abaddon</hi> and <hi>Apollyon</hi> in their hearts; thoſe<note n="h" place="margin">Mat. 7.15.</note> 
               <hi>Wolves in ſheeps cloathing,</hi> thoſe Serpents, that<note n="i" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.6.</note> creep unawares into ſecret Chambers, beguiling<note n="i" place="margin">2 Tim. 3.6.</note> unſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tled, and<note n="k" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> 
               <hi>unſtable ſouls;</hi> whether under the habit of Carpenters, of Seamen, of Butchers, of Cooks, of Coach men, or any ſort of Mechanicks, or indeed of what not, ſo be they may gain<note n="l" place="margin">Mat. 23.15.</note> 
               <hi>Proſelytes,</hi> and make them ten times more the children of Hell, then they were before; moſt Pernicious Incendiaries, not only in a Church, but in a State; and beleeve it, brethren, if the Magiſtrate do not early root out them (ſo ſoon as they may be unmasked and detected) they will, if poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, extirpate the Magiſtrate; <hi>Sunt Homines multorum nominum, ſed non boni nominis,</hi> they are men of many names, as may beſt advantage their occaſions, but real<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly of no good name or repute. In a word, Deal faithfully for God, for the true Religion, and for the quiet of your Country, by preſerving it from Rapines, Robbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Adulteryes, or whatever elſe may defile the Land: <hi>Take heed, and do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for all you Jurers of a ſubordinate Rank,<note place="margin">Advice to the Pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ty Jury and Witneſſes.</note> 
               <hi>Take heed what you do;</hi> and now, <hi>let the fear of the Lord be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:101120:23"/>you;</hi> be not like Oſtriches, to ſwallow down Iron; bring your hearts to the temper of <hi>Joſiah</hi>'s be<note n="l" place="margin">2 King. 22.19</note> tender in the matter of ſwearing, and learn to<note place="margin">Eccleſ 9.2. 1 Sam. 14.26.</note> fear an Oath; Remember who ſaid, <hi>The land mourns becauſe of Oaths, Jer:</hi> 23.10. When ſo me unadviſedly, others continually, and as it were by cuſtome, make an Oath an Interjection of filling of all their ſpeeches, and to ſerve to cloſe up the empty <hi>hiatus</hi> of their broken ſentences; Yea, which thereby come, as one expreſſeth it, to a <hi>Diabetica paſſio</hi> of ſwearing, ſo that Oaths run from them, and they feel them not: <hi>Joſhuah,</hi> who had the Authority, choſe out<note n="n" place="margin">Joſh. 3.12. and 4.2.</note> twelve worthy men out of the twelve Tribes, to ſerve their Country; have regard that there be no<note n="o" place="margin">Job. 6 70.</note> 
               <hi>Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>das</hi> among your twelve; he bore the<note n="p" place="margin">Joh. 12.6.</note> Bag, and for ſil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver<note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 27.4.</note> betrayed Innocent Blood; let there be none like <hi>Jezabels</hi> Knights of the Poſt, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 21.8, 9, 10. who by Impudent Perjury, through the wicked Subordination of a quean, occaſioned the ſhedding of Innocent Blood, and the Injurious Uſurpation of anothers Inheritance: If any particular hath been diſcovered in this kind, ſhake him off from your company, as <hi>Paul</hi> did the<note n="r" place="margin">Act. 28.5.</note> 
               <hi>Viper</hi> off from his hand; <hi>Qui ſemel malus fuit, ſemper praeſumi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur eſſe malus, in eodem genere,</hi> ſaith the Civill Law; He is no more to be truſted, in the ſame kind: In ſhort, Let not that, which is appointed of God to decide and<note n="ſ" place="margin">Heb 6.16.</note> end Controverſies among your Neighbours, be made, by any ſecret, malevolent, or revengefull intentions, the beginning of a greater<note n="t" place="margin">Hoſ. 4.1.</note> Controverſie, between God, and your own ſouls: <hi>Take heed, let the fear of the Lord be up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on you;</hi> Tremble to conteſt the<note n="u" place="margin">Joh. 21.17.</note> Omniſcient, ſoul-fear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching<note n="*" place="margin">Pſal. 44.21. Pſal. 7.9. Act. 1 24. Rom 8.27</note> God to a falſity; that God whom you ſo pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voke, will not hold you<note n="x" place="margin">Exod 20 7.</note> guiltleſſe: bring not then the<note n="y" place="margin">Zech. 5.3, 4.</note> curſe of God upon your ſouls, or into your houſes, by<note n="z" place="margin">Zech. 8.17.</note> falſe or by<note n="*" place="margin">Eccleſ. 5.2.</note> raſh ſwearing, Wherefore endeavor ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to be like to the Sun, and Moon in the Heavens, as<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 89.36, 37.</note> faithfull Witneſſes, <hi>Take heed, and do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly,<note place="margin">Advice to the Lawyers.</note> I might ſay alſo to you Lawyers, <hi>Take heed
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:101120:23"/>what yee do, and let the fear of the Lord be upon you:</hi> O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen your mouth, and plead the cauſe of the poor and needy, <hi>Prov.</hi> 31.9. Let the<note n="b" place="margin">Job 31 20.</note> Loyns of the deſolate Wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow, and the Bowels of the<note n="d" place="margin">Lam. 5.3.</note> Fatherleſſe Orphan, bleſs you, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82.3, 4. A Widow by your Law, is called <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cta,</hi> one left and expoſed to Injury, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith the Greek Proverb, When the Oak (the man) falleth, every one will be fetching of wood, and <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſaith <hi>Heſychius,</hi> is from <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one in the dark, or, under clouds, or, as <hi>Photinus,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, one that hath no helper; wherefore do you defend both: And yet I may not conceal, but that there have been ſome, who becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> (1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.) forbade the <hi>Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthians</hi> to go to Law one with another, and to wran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle about trifles, being Chriſtians, before<note n="*" place="margin">Hoc loco non ſimpticitèr vetat judicio conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dere propter res temporarias, ſed Corinthios re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prchendit, quòd impatientes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent nimiùm, ac inſupè malas cauſas in judicia [Ethnicorum] afferrent, &amp; in cis ità ſe gere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent, ut mag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nam praeberent occaſionem Eth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nicis vituperan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Evangelium. <hi>Bullinger. ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſ. Anabapt.</hi> lib. <hi>5.</hi> cap. <hi>4.</hi>
               </note> Infidel Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, whereby the Apoſtle meant only the Correction of a diſorder, and the avoiding of ſcandall; would yet, by a diſtortion of that Text, from a falſe Topick of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buſe, have the whole profeſſion it ſelf totally aboliſhed; not pondering the mean while, the hazard of what they poſſeſſe by that Precipitant, and (I had almoſt ſaid) Whimſicall wiſh; not conſidering the excellency of our Engliſh Lawes, tempered with ſo great equanimity, that on the one ſide, they be not like <hi>Draco's</hi> Lawes, writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten in blood, and altogether ſavouring of cruelty; nor on the other ſide, Illuſory, and light, ſavouring of vani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty. O, ſay ſuch Rooters, if the Client prove not a <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rund in Do,</hi> the Lawyer will ſoon become a <hi>Gerund in Dum:</hi> They deal by their Clients as Muſicians do by their Sackbuts, contract or diſtend their Cauſes, as the Fee ſtrengthens the breath; and in ſnarling language com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare them to thoſe Creatures, that having ſwallowed one gobbet, ſtare again in your faces, as if they had received none at all; like the<note n="e" place="margin">Prov. 30.15.16.</note> grave or the barren womb, they ſtill cry, Give, Give, and yet are not ſatisfied; and as they ſay of Bears, there is no ſuch deformed lump, but with their tongues they can lick it into ſome faſhion, and
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:101120:24"/>can eaſily ſmooth even the rougheſt ſtone: Such, and the like are the flowers of theſe mens Rhetorick, or rather the purulent excreations of their corrupt lungs, fitteſt for them to reſume, who firſt diſgorged them: for my ſelf, I might well bluſh under ſuch kind of Oratory, leſt you might regeſt upon me, as they did, <hi>Luke</hi> 11.45. <hi>Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, thus ſaying, thou reproacheſt us alſo:</hi> But it is not for me to turne an Exhortation into a Satyre, or to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe my ſelf in the ſtyle of the ſtage: the times require a Character of Love, not of any ſuch indiſcreet, or in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>temperate Zeal; I ſhould rather vindicate your Honor, (chiefly if you plead for ours, and our rights) then aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſe that Noble Profeſſion, which is of that<note n="f" place="margin">Job 9.21.</note> age, that its well able to ſpeak for it ſelf: Go on then, and<note n="g" place="margin">Pſal. 45.4.</note> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper; up, and be<note n="h" place="margin">1 Chron. 22.16</note> doing good, that your Country, and your<note n="i" place="margin">Act 13.36.</note> Generation may<note n="h" place="margin">1 Chron. 22.16</note> praiſe you; <hi>Take heed, and do it.</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Zeph. 3.19.</note>
            </p>
            <p>Fourthly:<note place="margin">Advice to the Clergy.</note> and laſtly, As in that Marriage Feaſt, where Chriſt himſelf was a gueſt, at <hi>Cana</hi> in <hi>Galiee,</hi> the<note n="l" place="margin">Joh. 2.10.</note> good wine was kept till laſt;<note n="m" place="margin">Deut. 32.2.</note> I ſhall, in all Reverentiall modeſty crave the favor to drop a word or two upon my reverend brethren of the Miniſtry: For, bleſſed be God, (notwithſtanding the interpoſition of ſome<note n="n" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Jude ver. 12</note> clouds without water) we yet ſee ſome ſhining lights ſtanding in their<note n="o" place="margin">Mat. 5.14, 15</note> Candleſticks, and it were a thouſand pities, but it ſhould be ſo ſtill: We read, that there were<note n="p" place="margin">Exod. 37.23.</note> Snuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers in Gods Tabernacle, that where the lights did burn but dimly, they might be amended; but I find no mention there made of Extinguiſhers. And here, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> ſaid, in an humble renuence to our Saviour, <hi>I have need to be baptiſed of thee,</hi>
               <note n="q" place="margin">Mat. 3.14.</note> 
               <hi>and comeſt thou to me?</hi> So I being more fit to take, then to give counſell this way; for I know the Schools determine, that an Angel of an Inferiour Hierarchy cannot illuminate one of a Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riour; Therefore, I would not preſume to inform, but only deſire to inflame my Reverend Brethren. Let us <hi>take heed what we do,</hi> and <hi>let the fear of the Lord be upon
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:101120:24"/>you:</hi> Learning is, or hath been of late years, in the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Tropick of <hi>Cancer,</hi> but when the Sun is at the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt, it is obſerved by Philoſophers, that the Fountains below are coldeſt: There is often more affectation of knowledge in the brain, then any zealous fervent,<note n="r" place="margin">2 Theſ. 2.10.</note> Af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection in the heart; even as it was at the firſt, the Tree of<note n="ſ" place="margin">Gen. 3.6.</note> Knowledge, was preferred to the Tree of Life: I ſhall not enlarge on this occaſion, only let us keep to the proper motion of our own Orbs: then ſhall we with Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority ſpeak what we do, when we do what we ſpeak: Let us be heard often, and ſeen ſeldome, and when we are ſeen, appear as ſome Rare and Beneficent Stars; and becauſe the Eye anticipates the Ear among the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conſtant Vulgar, (with whom its<note n="t" place="margin">Mat. 21.9.</note> 
               <hi>Hoſanna</hi> one day, and<note n="u" place="margin">Mark 15.13, 14 and Luke 23.21.</note> 
               <hi>Crucifie</hi> another, <hi>Neutrum modò, mas modò vul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gus</hi>) Let our Lives dazle, whom our Doctrine will not enlighten: Its poſſible, ſoon to make our ſelves too cheap, ſith we find it in experience, how too much airing, like ſome fair coloured Silks, makes us loſe our gloſſe: and men will be apt to tell us, that we are like Barbars, who ſnip off the<note n="*" place="margin">James 1.21.</note> Superfluities of others naughtineſſe, whilſt we ſuffer our own locks to overgrow, and to deform our ſelves: In one word, If we poure the box of Piety, as of Precious<note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 133.2.</note> Oyntment, upon our owne heads firſt, it may from thence diſtill, and trickle down to the very skirts of our garments, to the very meaneſt of our Hearers. And thus, Let us take heed to our ſelves, and doe.</p>
            <p>To conclude this whole Exhortation: To all this peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple in generall let me ſay as the Scripture doth,<note n="y" place="margin">Pſal. 34.14. 1 Pet. 3.11.</note> 
               <hi>Eſchew e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill, and do good,</hi> ſeek not death in the error of your lives, but<note n="z" place="margin">Deut. 30.19.</note> chuſe the wayes of life, in purſuing your peace with God; which is a <hi>Dicotomy,</hi> that makes up the <hi>Plerophory</hi> of a good Chriſtian: Labor to be <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, Every one to be<note n="*" place="margin">2 Cor. 1.12. Col. 3.23.</note> Entire in his Affections,<note n="a" place="margin">Pſal. 119.6, 7.</note> Univer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſall in his Obedience; Let every one be what he ſeems,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:101120:25"/>or elſe ſeem what he is; and, as the Church is ſaid <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.11. to have made her Borders of Gold, with ſtuds of Silver, have the beſt ſide inwards.</p>
            <p>Stand faſt in that Chriſtian<note n="b" place="margin">Gal. 5.1.</note> Liberty, wherewith Chriſt hath made you free, onely uſe it not as a<note n="c" place="margin">1 Pet. 2.16.</note> 
               <hi>Cloak of Maliciouſneſſe,</hi> or as an<note n="d" place="margin">Gal. 5.13.</note> 
               <hi>occaſion of the fleſh; but by love ſerve one another:</hi> Take heed of<note n="e" place="margin">1 Tim. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>Seducing ſpirits,</hi> eſpecially of the White Divell, who ſometimes transformes himſelfe into an<note n="f" place="margin">2 Cor. 11.14.</note> Angel of Light; beware of thoſe<note n="g" place="margin">S Jude ver. 13.</note> 
               <hi>Wandring Stars,</hi> whoſe faint blazes, ſhall never bee able to out ſhine the Ancient and Pure Light of the<note n="h" place="margin">Mal. 4.2.</note> 
               <hi>Sun of Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſneſſe,</hi> or that <hi>Faith which was</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <note n="i" place="margin">S. Jude ver. 3.</note> 
               <hi>once</hi> for all <hi>delivered to the Saints.</hi> Give not the Right Hand of<note n="k" place="margin">Gal. 2.9.</note> Fellowſhip to ſuch who would withdraw you from the Ordinances of Chriſt, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king a Religion of wax, depending onely upon the traine of their own affaires; ſuch as thoſe who fit Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion to their Wills, not their Wills to the true Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion; not bringing their froward Conſciences to the<note n="l" place="margin">Gal. 6.16. and Phil. 3.16.</note> Rule of the Word Orthodoxly expounded but often, the Word miſtaken, if not too much<note n="m" place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> wre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted, to their owne miſ-informed Conſciences: O lean not to your owne<note n="n" place="margin">Prov. 3.5.</note> Underſtandings, and ever ſuſpect that Doctrine which tends to cheriſh the<note n="o" place="margin">Gal. 5.13. <hi>S.</hi> Jude ver. 4. Pſal. 53.1. Ezek. 20 44.</note> Corruptions of Nature; which is all for the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes and Priviledges, but nothing at all for the Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepts of the Goſpel; all for Comfort, but for<note n="p" place="margin">Pſal. 2 3. Luk. 17.10.</note> Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty not at all: Who dimidiate Chriſt, would have him onely by halfes, to be <hi>Jeſus</hi> for a Saviour, but reject him from being a Lord and a King, to Rule or<note n="q" place="margin">Luk. 19.27.</note> Raign over them: Such as they reaſon much from the Power of God: what he [can] do, name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, without the ordinary means; not from his<note n="r" place="margin">Rom 12.2.</note> Wil revealed, the ſole<note n="ſ" place="margin">Phil. 3.16. and Gal. 6.16.</note> Canon of all our Actions: A meer Paralogiſme, and groundleſſe kind of reaſoning.
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:101120:25"/>Who queſtions, but that God [can] give wings to men to fly withall, for he hath done it unto Eagles? but [will] God do it unto men? this were to pervert the Order and Beauty of his Creation, which God (the<note n="t" place="margin">1 Cor. 14.33.</note> God of Order) will not do; no nor ordinarily bring a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny to the end, which is Salvation, without the preciſeſt uſe of the ordinary means, which is Sanctification: And indeed, if there be any, who think themſelves too good for the means; the means (in Gods formidable Judgement) may, in the Event, become too good for them, <hi>Amos</hi> 8.11. <hi>Matth.</hi> 21.43. The ſumme of all that I have now to ſay, amounts to this; So live, and ſtrive for Holineſſe, as if thou hadſt no mean of Salva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion but that; and yet ſo reſt and rely upon the Merits of Jeſus Chriſt, as if thou hadſt no holineſſe at all: And thus let the <hi>fear of the Lord be upon you</hi> all, <hi>Take heed, and do it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have no more to add, ſave only to aſſure you (thus doing) of a moſt ample and glorious Remuneration of all your Gracious Endeavors, by the<note n="u" place="margin">2 Tim. 4 8. and Gen 18.25.</note> Righteous Judge of all the world; no mans Righteous<note n="*" place="margin">Heb. 6.10.</note> Labour was e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver in<note n="*" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.58</note> vain in the Lord, or went<note n="x" place="margin">Gen. 15.1.</note> 
               <note n="x" place="margin">Pſal. 19.11. &amp; 31.19 &amp; 58.11 Prov. 24.14. Iſal 40.10. &amp; 62.11 Mat. 5.12. Col. 3.24. 2 Ep Joh. 8. Rev 22.12.</note> unrewarded; Yea thus doing, ye ſhall be advanced, not only to a more neer Communion with God in the Beatificall Viſion, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo unto a moſt precellent honor before the world, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to ſit on the Throne with Chriſt himſelf, judging the world, yea Angels, as ye read 1 <hi>Corinth.</hi> 6.2, 3. though not Authoritatively (that<note n="y" place="margin">Phil. 2.9, 10.</note> Exaltation being given by God the Father, to his Son Chriſt, as Man, as the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compence of his Humiliation, <hi>John</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 22, 27) Yet as Aſſeſſors, and Approvers of that Juſt Sentence, which by<note n="z" place="margin">Joh. 5.27.</note> Commiſſion from God, the Lord Chriſt ſhall then<note n="a" place="margin">Mat 25.34.</note> pronounce upon the world. I ſhall cite only one ſingle Text very appoſite to this purpoſe, and ſo cloſe up all: It is extant in the nineteenth Chapter of Saint <hi>Matthew,</hi> verſe the twenty eighth, compared with <hi>Luk.</hi> 22.30.
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:101120:26"/>
               <hi>And Jeſus ſaid unto them, Verily I ſay unto you, that yee which have followed me; In the Regeneration, when the Son of Man ſhall ſit in the Throne of his Glory, yee alſo ſhall ſit upon Twelve Thrones, judging the Twelve Tribes of Iſrael.</hi> A ſhort Paraphraſe, upon which words ſhall now terminate both my Sermon, and (as I fear) your wearyed Patience.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Yee which have followed me</hi>] that is, <hi>all yee,</hi> not my Twelve Apoſtles only, but all other ſincere <hi>Natha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neels,</hi> and<note n="b" place="margin">Joh. 1.47.</note> 
               <hi>Iſraelites</hi> indeed. <hi>Which have followed me,</hi> to wit, in things capable of imitation: Not in the Acts of Mediatorſhip, which no meer Creature, and onely Chriſt himſelfe could do, nor in acts of Omnipotence, Infiniteneſſe, or of miraculous Nature, and ſuch like. But in the Morall Actions of obedience. <hi>In the Rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration</hi>] Which word is not, as<note n="c" place="margin">Hilar. <hi>Can.</hi> 26 <hi>in</hi> Matth.</note> 
               <hi>Hillary,</hi> and ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers miſtook, to be expounded in this particular Text of that Spirituall Regeneration, by which we are born again of water, and of the Holy Ghoſt, <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.5. begun in this life, becauſe it is ſaid here, That the Apoſtles and Saints ſhall ſit upon Thrones judging, which we read not of at all in this world, where they were rather themſelves judged: But this <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, or Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration, is to be underſtood of the<note n="d" place="margin">Act. 3.21.</note> Reſtauration of all things, in the generall Reſurrection. <hi>Sic enim caro no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtra regenerabitur, per incorruptionem, quemadmodum eſt anima noſtra regenerata per Fidem,</hi> as Saint<note n="e" place="margin">
                  <hi>S.</hi> Aug. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>c.</hi> 5. <hi>De Civ. Dei</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guſtin</hi> elegantly: For our fleſh is, as it were, Regene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate from the grave, by Incorruptions; as our ſoul is regenerate from the ſtate of nature, by Faith and Holi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe: So that this Expreſſion apperatains not, as<note n="f" place="margin">Joh Gerard <hi>Tom.</hi> 8. <hi>loc. com. c.</hi> 1.</note> 
               <hi>Gerard</hi> well interprets, to this deſcription of the Subject, or of the Manner and Forme, How the Apoſtles and Saints do follow Chriſt; but to the Determination of time, which is added to the Predicate, and ſhewes when the Retribution of Glory ſhall be given unto the Saints; Namely, then, when the <hi>Son of Man
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:101120:26"/>ſhall ſit upon the</hi>
               <note n="g" place="margin">Mat. 25.31.</note> 
               <hi>Throne of his Glory.</hi> By <hi>Twelve Thrones,</hi> and <hi>Twelve Tribes,</hi> putting a certain num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for an uncertaine (as is not unuſuall in Holy Writ) are meant the whole number of thoſe who ſhall be Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and alſo be judged; for elſe the Twelve Apoſtles only ſhould be Judges, and none but Jewes of the Twelve Tribes be judged; whereas Saint <hi>Paul</hi> affirmes, that all other Saints ſhall likewiſe Judge (in the ſenſe but now named) even all the world: O Heavenly Dig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity! O Honor Incomprehenſible!</p>
            <p>So then, my Dearly Beloved, and<note n="b" place="margin">Phil. 4.1.</note> 
               <hi>longed for in the Lord,</hi> let now but the <hi>fear of the Lord be upon you,</hi> in this Kingdome of Grace here; then may you even when the laſt<note n="i" place="margin">1 Cor. 15.52</note> Trump ſhall ſound, and the dead ſhall riſe incor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruptible, lift<note n="k" place="margin">Luke 21.28.</note> up your heads with joy in the Kingdome of Immortall Glory hereafter, unto all Eternity.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Which God of his Infinite mercy grant unto us all, for the ſake of the Son of his Love, Jeſus Chriſt the Righteous, for whom our ſouls do bleſs Thee, O Heavenly Father; and on whom we anchor all our Hopes, and to whom with Thee and thy ever Bleſſed Spirit, Trinity in <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity, and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity in Trinity, be rendred and aſcribed, as is moſt due, from the bottom of all our Hearts, all poſſible Praiſe, and Glory, from henceforth and for evermore.</hi> Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
